<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Usury explain'd, or, Conscience quieted in the case of putting out mony at interest by Philopenes.</title>
            <author>J. D. (John Dormer), 1636-1700.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1695</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 141 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 64 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A70290</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H3249</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R12079</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12841416</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12841416</idno>
            <idno type="VID">39313</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A70290)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 39313)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 715:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Usury explain'd, or, Conscience quieted in the case of putting out mony at interest by Philopenes.</title>
                  <author>J. D. (John Dormer), 1636-1700.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 116 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by D.E. ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1695/6.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata: prelim. p. [2].</note>
                  <note>Attributed to John Dormer the Jesuit (pseud. of John Huddleston). cf. DNB.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Interest --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:39313:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:39313:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>USURY Explain'd; OR, <hi>Conſcience Quieted in the Caſe</hi> OF Putting out Mony AT INTEREST.</p>
            <p>By <hi>PHILOPENES.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>D. E.</hi> in <hi>Fetter-Lane.</hi> 1695/6.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:39313:2"/>
            <head>ERRATA'S.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 10, <hi>l.</hi> 7. del. and, <hi>p.</hi> 13. <hi>l.</hi> 2. r. Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fixing. <hi>l.</hi> 22. r. Operation. <hi>p.</hi> 16. <hi>l.</hi> 7. r. Mutuare. <hi>l.</hi> 15. r. lend. <hi>l.</hi> 21. r. to Mony, r. to Place, <hi>l.</hi> 25. r. ſome truths, <hi>l.</hi> 16. r. truths I think, <hi>p.</hi> 27. <hi>l.</hi> 24. r. <hi>Aedil. p.</hi> 29. <hi>l.</hi> 9. r. a perſon. <hi>p.</hi> 33. <hi>l.</hi> r. r. then. <hi>l.</hi> 10. r. § <hi>Nota. l.</hi> 14. r. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſura. l.</hi> 15. r. <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractus. p.</hi> 35. <hi>l.</hi> 17. r. a fort. <hi>p.</hi> 37. <hi>l.</hi> 22. r. <hi>quaerat, ſorte minime. l.</hi> 29. r. <hi>Proventus. p.</hi> 37. <hi>l.</hi> 4. r. conſiſts, <hi>p.</hi> 42. <hi>l.</hi> 25. r. Illation. <hi>p.</hi> 50. <hi>l.</hi> 16. r. exclude. <hi>p.</hi> 51. <hi>l.</hi> 26. r. <hi>quintus. p.</hi> 52. <hi>l.</hi> 1. r. Partner, <hi>p.</hi> 53. <hi>l.</hi> 4. r. <hi>Bullarium, p.</hi> 55. <hi>l.</hi> 19. r. a hundred, <hi>p.</hi> 62. <hi>l.</hi> 12. r. ſhould, <hi>p.</hi> 74. <hi>l.</hi> 13 r. ſin of Uſury, <hi>l.</hi> 25. r. an Actual. <hi>p.</hi> 76. <hi>l.</hi> 15. r. at a Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable <hi>p.</hi> 79. <hi>l.</hi> 6. r. borrower, accrues, <hi>p.</hi> 70. <hi>l.</hi> 21. r. <hi>debuerat, p.</hi> 75. <hi>l.</hi> 27. r. Owner <hi>p.</hi> 102 <hi>l.</hi> 1022. 5. after <hi>9th,</hi> dI: even</p>
         </div>
         <div type="printer_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:39313:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE PRINTER TO THE Courteous Reader</head>
            <p>GEntle Reader, in compliance with my Calling, I preſent thee with a ſmall Treatiſe, upon the Caſe of Putting out Mony at Uſe, The Subject is of a Publick concern, and the Preſs is ordered to the Publick good. Written Papers, are like Spirits, appear to ſome, and not to others, and often Prove illuſions. The Publick eye is the quickeſt and the ſureſt in diſcerning good, from evil.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:39313:3"/>
            <p>The Author who writ, what I now Print, is no farther Known to me, than by the Name of <hi>Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penes,</hi> a lover of Poverty, or a friend of the Poor. If he be, what his name implies, The fitter he is, to diſcourſe impartially a Point, in which Reaſon alone can concern him; I hope he will not take it in evil Part, that I ſet forth for ſome ſmall Advantage, what for more than a year, has paſt thro' ſeveral hands; That were to blame his own Judgment, in letting it be ſeen by ſo many, or to give ſuſpicion of ſome dark Deſign: by avoiding the Publick.</p>
            <p>If what he writes be True, 'tis one of thoſe Truths, which ought not to be conceal'd, nor hidden un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Buſhel; that were envious. If erroneous, not to ſecure Error by diſcovery, that were uncharitable. If he fears Truth may diſpleaſe ſome,
<pb facs="tcp:39313:3"/>he might as well deſire to put out all light, as offenſive to weaker ſights, unuſeful to the Blind, and unaccepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to ſuch, as wilfully ſhut their Eyes.</p>
            <p>The Book is but ſhort, well if it be clear; ſhort as it is, Divines, Lawyers, and all concern'd in Mony; may find in it ſomewhat for their Turns. Be it what it will, take it for what it is: The Print is only mine, and may be thine, too at a ſmall Charge, <hi>Farewell.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="author_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:39313:4"/>
            <head>THE Author TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>ZEal when Kindled by Divine Love, temper'd with Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, fed by the Spirit of Meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and govern'd by Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion cheriſhes Piety and Obſervance. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpation of Rigor, carried on, with ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes of Fervor, <hi>Not according to Knowledge, Rom.</hi> the 10th. diſquiets both. To make a Sin, of no Sin, is as irregular, as to make no Sin, of a Sin. To declare unlawful, what conſiſts with Conſcience, breeds an underva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue of the Declarer, no leſs than if he declare lawful, what Conſcience con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demns.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:39313:4"/>
            <p>Conſcience cenſures nothing, but upon Evidence of Obligation; Prepoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of Mans Liberty, is ſo good a title, that it cannot be overthrown, but by a manifeſt Proof, of Gods re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraining it. To alledge a Command, for his not his, is to impoſe upon God and Man, the worſt of Preſumptions.</p>
            <p>Faith requires an Evidence of Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dibility, in reference to what we are to believe; and Part of that we are to believe, are the Rules of well and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Doing. Whence clearly enſues, a certainty muſt be had of thoſe Rules; For where a Rational Debate is admitted upon the whether, an Action be ſinful, or no, ſo as to leave it unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cided, Poſſeſſion of Liberty againſt Restraint, holds good in Reaſon and Law, where Poſſeſſion carries ſo great a Portion, that no man is oblig'd to relinquiſh it, before evidence brought in againſt him for its forfeiture, and ſentence Pronounced in due form, by
<pb facs="tcp:39313:5"/>a Competent Judge. Without this whoever diſturbs, the quiet Poſſeſſor, is guilty of Violating the Peace. This diſcourſe I have in Occaſions Promot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed againſt Modern Pretended Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers, in Point of Religion, in the Preſent Caſe, I renew it.</p>
            <p>A ſettled Practice, of Putting out of Mony, has been long in Poſſeſſion with all Ranks and Qualities, ſuch as take upon them to Reform it, muſt Produce Evidence, and Sentence gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven by a Lawful Judge againſt it; whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther any Verdict has yet paſt to that Purpoſe, be your ſelf the Arbitor, after a due Peruſal, of what I ſhall impartially ſet down, in this ſhort Tract.</p>
            <p>My Method is to Diſcourſe the Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in hand, as to the Laws of Nature, Scripture, and Church. I wiſh my Endeavours may anſwer my Intentions, or at leaſt, that my Intentions, may ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie my Endeavours, in Caſe they an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer not thy Expectation. Farewel.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:39313:5"/>
            <head>THE CONTENTS.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <label>PART. 1.</label> AS to the Law of Nature.
  <list>
                     <item>
                        <label>CHAP. 1.</label> The Caſe Conſidered as to the nature of Mony.</item>
                     <item>
                        <label>CHAP. 2.</label> The Original Notion of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury, with its Names.</item>
                     <item>
                        <label>CHAP. 3.</label> The ſtrict Definition of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury.</item>
                     <item>
                        <label>CHAP. 4.</label> Aſſertions drawn from the ſaid Definition.</item>
                     <item>
                        <label>CHAP. 5.</label> Whether the Law of England Juſtifie the Caſe.</item>
                     <item>
                        <label>CHAP. 6.</label> Whether Mony be capable of being Lett.</item>
                     <item>
                        <label>CHAP. 7.</label> Of the Obligation of Lending.</item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:39313:6"/>
                     <item>
                        <label>CHAP. 8.</label> Titles alledged by Divines for the Lawfulneſs of taking Intereſt.</item>
                     <item>
                        <label>CHAP. 9.</label> Whether in ſome Caſe it ſtand with Law and Conſcience, to take more than the Current?</item>
                     <item>
                        <label>CHAP. 10.</label> Of the Briſtol Bargain, Pawn-Brocage, and Intereſt upon Intereſt.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>PART. 2.</label> 
                  <hi>As to Scripture.</hi>

                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <label>CHAP. 1.</label> 
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury Conſidered as to the Old Testament</item>
                     <item>
                        <label>CHAP. 2.</label> The ſame Conſidered as to the New.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>PART. 3.</label> 
                  <hi>As to the Church.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <label>CHAP. 1.</label> Teſtimonies of the Latin Fathers exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined.</item>
                     <item>
                        <label>CHAP  2.</label> Teſtimonies of the Greek.</item>
                     <item>
                        <label>CHAP. 3.</label> Authorities of Councils.</item>
                     <item>
                        <label>CHAP. 4.</label> Authorities of Popes'</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>The Concluſion.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:39313:6"/>
            <head>PART. I. <hi>As to the Law of Nature.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I. <hi>The Caſe Conſidered as to the Nature of MONY.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>ARiſtotle</hi> defining Libera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>lib.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 1.</note> 
                  <hi>to be a Vertue mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derating the Love of Mony,</hi> and <hi>Prompting to ſpend, by the dictates of Reaſon.</hi> Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Name of Mony, comprehends all things priz'd by Mony, as the ſtanding Meaſure of their Worth. The preſent Diſcourſe admits not of ſo much Lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, but confines it ſolely, to the being the Meaſure of Valuation, and Price of
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:39313:7"/>Wares; ſo becoming the common In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument of Sales and Purchaſes, the Soul of Traffick, and the Life of Markets.</p>
               <p>As to its Origin not over Noble, I find it to have been the Child of Want, tho' ſince become the Parent of Abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance. When all other Creatures bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing different Coins, iſſued out of the Mint, if I may be ſo bold to ſay, of nothing: No Mony appear'd, which perchance may have been a Reaſon, why the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent brib'd our firſt Parents to Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion, not with Mony, but Ambition, and Pleaſure.</p>
               <p>All other Beings had God for their Creator, Mony, as to its Form, was the Creature of Man, and that only after his Fall, being multiplied upon Earth; Diviſions of Property then, enter'd the World, from whence ſprung a Neceſſity of Commerce; <hi>First,</hi> By Bartering one thing for another: In ſucceſs of Time, Trade improving, a Current Meaſure, for the Price of Things, was judg'd re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſit, and therefore ſettled by each Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perior, in his Reſpective Dominion, and admitted by Communities. So that, as the firſt intercourſe of Trade, was enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:39313:7"/>by Exchange of one thing, for another, Mony became the vicar, as it were, of all things, And by conſequence, was deſign'd to be of no leſs Profit. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe the Exchange of other Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities for Mony, would have been unequal, in giving what might Produce Gain for Mony, which ſhould afford None.</p>
               <p>Such was the firſt Inſtitution of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, Riſing by Degrees to that ſway that <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelf,
<note place="margin">Salluſt. in Jug.</note> with its grave ſtately Senat, would have been unſubdu'd, had a Purchaſer, of ſufficient Wealth, appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed before it. This moves no ſmall won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in me, that Mony vulgarly ſhould paſs for barren, and unfruitful, ſeeing it renders to its Owner, whatever Nature produces. For tho' of it ſelf, or rather its matter yield nothing; Yet by the Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficial Being it has from Man, it gives Profit at leaſt equal to other Productions of Art, affording Rent, for the uſe of them. Nay brings in much greater en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, to the skilful Mannager.</p>
               <p>The Mountebank in St. <hi>Auſtine,</hi> to raiſe expectation, took upon him to
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:39313:8"/>tell the People,
<note place="margin">De Trin.</note> what was each ones wiſh and deſire, Curioſity having gathered a Numerous gaping Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditory, he acquits himſelf of his Promiſe, ſaying; <hi>They would all buy cheap, and ſell dear.</hi> This aſſuredly is the conſtant intent of ſuch as expend, to encreaſe Mony in its Uſe. For he that buys cheap, and ſelis dear, in what he buys, enſures his Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal with Profit; ſo that to receive ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage for Mony, without ſinking the Principal, is but a ſequel of its being the Price of Wares. On this account I gueſs, a Mony'd Man, is ſaid to have a good <hi>Fund,</hi> from the Latin <hi>Fundus</hi> a Farm, or a good <hi>Stock,</hi> in token of its Fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs.</p>
               <p>Of what Metal the firſt Mony was, or whether of any, I were yet to learn, had I hopes of a Maſter to Teach me. But the quality of the Matter, is indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent to the character it bears. This gives it its worth, and Men may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow it upon Leather, Lead or other Materials in lieu of Gold, and Silver.</p>
               <p>Mony methinks, has much of the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of words, tho' not ſo frankly parted with. Both are Mans Tenants at Will,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:39313:8"/>both order'd to Interchange and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication, Words of thoughts, and Mony of things, neither to be falſified, but to be directed to the end, for which they were Fram'd, general Conveniency, and improvement. By a more or leſs Tendency, to this end, the good, or bad uſe, of either is determin'd. Now to decide whether the putting out of Mony at a modeſt Rate, drive at that end, or no, who can judge better, than the whole of a Nation.</p>
               <p>But Uſury intervenes Let him who advances ſo bold a Cenſure, Vouchſafe to mind, how in Number He's much out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voted, equall'd at leaſt in Wiſdom, and Probity by thoſe, who teach and Practice it, as <hi>Lawful.</hi> Theſe have open'd the law of Nature, Scripture, and Church, yet do not find it culpable; People find con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniency in a ready Circulation, Mony otherwiſe would lie buried with dead Trade, the generality would be the worſe, and no particular the better. Neither the nature of Mony then, nor its final cauſe the Publick good, do any ways op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the putting out of Mony at Uſe, but promote it, as much as the expoſing other
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:39313:9"/>Goods, of which, Mony is the Subſtitute. This might ſuffice, to the quieting a well meaning Conſcience, but a further diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of the Nature of Uſury is expected from me, to which now I proceed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II. <hi>The Original Notion of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury, with its NAMES.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>REſolving lately upon the pefor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of what, almoſt a year ſince, I had engag'd my Promiſe to the Inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of ſome Friends; it was my chance to fall in at the Stationers, with two ſhort Treatiſes of Uſury; the one writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by an Engliſh Knight, Sir <hi>Robert Filmer,</hi> and Publiſh'd by Sir <hi>Roger Twiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den,</hi> with his Addition of Preface; the other of a Reverend <hi>French</hi> Clergyman, Monſieur <hi>Du Tertre;</hi> I found them as oppoſit in the Point, as if they would even in this, have maintain'd the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal Feud, had the one Known the other.</p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:39313:9"/>
               <p>But <hi>Du Tertre's</hi> Rhetorick, takes its full Career againſt a Divine of his own Country, who it ſeems in a Letter, had joyn'd with our two Knights, in uphold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that no Uſury is Condemn'd by the Law of God, but ſuch as exacts upon the Poor. <hi>Du Tertre</hi> on the contrary ſeems to hold forth, that all Intereſt taken for Mony put Out, without ſinking the Principal is Uſury. Neither hits the mark of Truth: the Knights fall ſhort, and <hi>Du Tertre</hi> ſhoots over; to level my aim better</p>
               <p>I begin from the Name of Uſury de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riv'd from the Latin <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſura.</hi> And this in Property of ſpeech imports <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</hi> So that Uſury in ſtrictneſs of Terms, implies no more, then the uſe of Mony, in it ſelf unblameable. How then did ſo foul a Vice come by ſo fair a Name? You might as well enquire, why the Furies were call'd <hi>Eumenides.</hi> I know in Greek its called <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. for the reſemblance pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Intereſt has, with the grief of Child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>birth. In Hebrew its ſtiled <hi>Neſhec</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> The Bite of a Dog, in <hi>Chaldaick Cabu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia, an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndoing,</hi> yet by the Jews, it was alſo nam'd <hi>Tarbith</hi> an Increaſe. <hi>Ad Probri
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:39313:10"/>effugium, (In</hi> cap. 23. Deut.) ſays; <hi>à Lapide uti à Latinis, honeſto Nomine vocata eſt <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſura.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Wherefore my Inference is, That the gentle Name of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury,</hi> muſt cover ſore Aggrievances, and heavy Extortions, as the <hi>Greek,</hi> the <hi>Hebrew,</hi> and <hi>Chaldaick,</hi> give us to underſtand; but theſe are not to be found in our Caſe; This therefore muſt be clear of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury;</hi> a Monſterde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtable, even to Heathens, a wonder it ſhould be ſo familiarly entertain'd, and welcom'd among Chriſtians, as is the Practice of Putting out Mony, a Token of its different Nature, from what thoſe Names imply, which having premis'd; I ſhall now endeavour to Dive after its Origin; Reaſon, and Hiſtory, diſcovers it to me, for ſuch as follows.</p>
               <p>Upon the firſt Imploying of Mony, of which probably he had moſt, who had the moſt to Sell, by Changing a Stock of Goods into a Stock of Coin, ſome En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groſſing the greater Share, put others in Neceſſity of Borrowing; then Avarice in the Lenders, produc'd Oppreſſions, with other evil Arts, of unlawful Gain, for the Uſe of what was, or ought to
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:39313:10"/>have been Lent, according to the Law, of Natural Charity.</p>
               <p>Such was the Proceeding, of the weal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thier <hi>Romans,</hi> with the Commonalty, as is to be ſeen in Hiſtory, to the no ſmall Diſturbance of that only then Infant Commonwealth, let one Example ſuffice. The horrid ſight of a ſtout old Soldier, ſcourg'd and gor'd with his own Blood for failure of Paying Intereſt, at the Time prefix'd, enrag'd the People to a furious Sedition. The like perhaps, may have paſſed, among the <hi>Jews;</hi> We have a kind of Precedent. 4 <hi>King. Chap.</hi> 4. Where the Widow to <hi>Eliſha</hi> ſays: <hi>Ecce creditor venit ut collat duos filios ad ſerviendum ſibi. Behold the Creditor is come, to take away my two Sons, to ſerve him.</hi> Exorbitant Rigour, for a Debt, which conſidering the Condition, of the Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, of a Poor Prophet, was not proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly very great.</p>
               <p>Uſages ſo cruel, could not but excite a horror of Uſurers, even in ſuch, as by the Law of Nature, govern'd themſelves; Uſe-Mony therefore, was by the <hi>Romans</hi> in the 12 Tables ſtinted to 12 <hi>per Cent.</hi> then to 6, after to 3; and finally in the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:39313:11"/>time of <hi>Gemutius</hi> Tribune, to remove all occaſions of like Encroachments, a Prohibition of Uſe-Mony was Publiſhed, in favour of the People. No leſs was put in Execution by <hi>Agis,</hi> the <hi>Spartan,</hi> and not the <hi>Athenian</hi> General, as ſome have it, and ordering all the Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt-Books of Uſurers, to be burnt, in the Market-place. <hi>Ageſilaus</hi> applaud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing he had never ſeen a nobler Fire.</p>
               <p>But the Prohibition among the <hi>Romans,</hi> ſoon grew out of Date, and tho' renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by <hi>Caeſar,</hi> to ingratiate himſelf with the Commonalty: yet putting out Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny at Uſe, by Neceſſity was reviv'd, in his Succeſſor's Times, growing to the extravagant Heighth, of <hi>Cent. per Cent.</hi> if you may believe <hi>Accurſius,</hi> a Famous Civilian, Cited by Sir <hi>Roger Twiſden</hi> in his Preface. As for my Part, I queſtion not, but all Oppreſſions, Exactions, and Frauds, exerciſed in the putting out Mony, were included in Uſury, which may have been the Cauſe, why in the Days of Old, witneſs <hi>Cato,</hi> Thieves were Condemn'd to the Double, Uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers to the Quadruple: To which Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom, Peradventure, the Saying, (of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:39313:11"/>
                  <hi>Zacheus</hi> might relate (<hi>Luke</hi> 19.) <hi>Reddo quadruplum;</hi> you may ſee more in <hi>Covar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruvias, lib.</hi> 3. <hi>Variarum,</hi> c. 1. <hi>n.</hi> 5. of the averſion even Heathens had to Uſury.</p>
               <p>This to have been the true, and ſole Notion, of Uſury as Prohibited, was <hi>Calvin</hi>'s Opinion, with his Followers, amongſt which our two Knights, allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all Uſury, not render'd ſinful by op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing the Poor, but againſt Reaſon; It being no leſs Uſury, to take beyond what is due from any, for the Uſe of Mony; ſince Perſons of Fortune, tho' never ſo wealthy, have Right to what is juſt. I only infer, That a commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Rate, in the common Judgment of all Parties, can be no Uſury; taking U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury, as hitherto deſcrib'd from its Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, and expreſs'd by its Names. I come now, to its ſtrict Definition.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:39313:12"/>
               <head>CHAP. III. <hi>The Definition of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RY.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>SIr <hi>Robert Filmer</hi> ſportsin his firſt Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragraph, teazing Dr. <hi>Fenton,</hi> and in him ſome others of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> for their Definition of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury.</hi> I cannot excuſe the Dr. of ſome Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſeneſs. For where a word may ſignify differently, to take away Equivocation, one ſhould firſt diſtinguiſh, and then de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fine. This Method I ſhall obſerve with the antient Divines.</p>
               <p>Theſe make a three-fold Diviſion of Uſury. Firſt it may be taken, for a <hi>Gain</hi> which is Uſurious. 2dly, For a <hi>Bargain</hi> upon ſuch Gain. 3dly, For the <hi>Intention,</hi> or <hi>Will</hi> of ſuch a Bargain or Gain. The Firſt is term'd <hi>Actual <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury.</hi> The Second is <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury expreſs'd by Covenant.</hi> The Third is <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury purely Mental.</hi> The two Lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter derive their Malice, from the Firſt, as being the Object of both, all Promiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es or Intentions taking their Qualificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:39313:12"/>from the Action, Promiſed or In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended; Wherefore refixing the Word <hi>Covenant</hi> or <hi>Will,</hi> to the Definition of <hi>Actual <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury,</hi> all three will be Defin'd Thus.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury</hi> in the firſt Acceptance, is <hi>a Gain immediately for Lending, or for Mony Lent as Lent.</hi> Divines generally Agree in it. It's ſaid immediately for <hi>Lending or as Lent.</hi> To exclude all other Titles of Lucre, as <hi>Gratitude, Friendſhip</hi> in the Borrower, or other <hi>Conſiderations,</hi> here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after to be ſpecified. <hi>Gain</hi> therefore is the <hi>Genus;</hi> by the Reſt, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury</hi> is differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enced from other Acquiſitions. Hence of courſe follow the two other Defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, <hi>viz.</hi> The Second <hi>is a Covenant;</hi> the Third is <hi>a Will or Purpoſe of Gain pure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for Lending.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Sir <hi>Robert</hi> oppoſes thus: <hi>Gain undoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly is a falſe Genus, for certainly, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury is a ſin of Commiſſion, and therefore an Action of Opperation. So that Lucre or Gain, which is only a Paſſion or Product of Lending, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be the Genus of it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> How far Sir <hi>Robert</hi>'s Skill ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded in Law, I know not, His Logick certainly proves ſomewhat unfaithful to
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:39313:13"/>him. It's granted then that <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury</hi> is a Sin of <hi>Commiſſion,</hi> and an <hi>Action</hi> of <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration,</hi> if it ſo pleaſe him. And ſo is <hi>Gain for Lending.</hi> Neither is Gain, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mally, and ſtrictly ſpeaking, the imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate Product, of Lending, but of taking, and it includes <hi>Active</hi> and <hi>Paſſive; Active,</hi> naming the Perſon Gaining, <hi>Paſſive,</hi> by naming the Intereſt Gain'd; Gain then is an Acceptance of Intereſt, exclude the Acceptance, neither Lending, nor Mony, nor both together, will make up Gain. But not to be ſo ſcrupulous in Philoſophy. Grant Gain to be a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of Lending, it may be as well a Product of Selling, or Letting, why may not Gain then be drawn into a <hi>Genus,</hi> in reſpect of the ſeveral ways of Gaining, of which Gain by Lending is Uſury?</p>
               <p>He preſſes. <hi>Lending</hi> for <hi>Gain,</hi> is not <hi>Lending</hi> but <hi>Letting.</hi> Beſides the <hi>Gain</hi> is <hi>not for the Bare Act of Lending, but <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſing the thing Lent, that Men give <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The inſtance being made in Dr. <hi>Fentons</hi> Words, If I may believe the Knight, brings him in guilty, not only of Contradiction, which Sir <hi>Robert</hi> urges upon him, but of a very
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:39313:13"/>groſs Error in Morality. For if accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the <hi>Dr</hi>'s Definition, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury is a Covenant of Lucre for Lending,</hi> and Lend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for Lucre; be <hi>Letting,</hi> a Covenant for <hi>Letting,</hi> by conſequence is Uſury. A Poſition unheard of.</p>
               <p>To the Difficulty. <hi>Lending</hi> for Gain, is no <hi>Letting,</hi> but <hi>Lending;</hi> and <hi>Lending,</hi> and <hi>Letting</hi> eſſentially differ, as will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear more hereafter. <hi>Lending</hi> admits of no Recompence, by way of Juſtice. <hi>Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting</hi> do's, I willingly yield to the Addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that Gain, is not for the bare act of <hi>Lending;</hi> but the <hi>Lending</hi> we ſpeak of, includes both Act and thing as affected by the Act of <hi>Lending.</hi> For who Lends, and lends nothing? By <hi>Lending</hi> a thing, the Uſe of it is given, as it is not in <hi>Letting,</hi> and for what is given, to require Gain, is Uſury.</p>
               <p>Towards the full Intelligence of the Definition, it will not be amiſs, to open the two-fold Senſe of the Word <hi>Lend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> expreſs'd in <hi>Latin</hi> by two Verbs <hi>Mutuare,</hi> and <hi>Commodare,</hi> to Lend things, not to be conſum'd, in the Uſe, as a Horſe, or Houſe, with an Obligation, that the ſame individually be reſtored
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:39313:14"/>is what correſponds to the <hi>Latin Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dare,</hi> to lend things which are Spent, in the Uſe; as Corn, Wine, and Mony, with a tie of having as much reſtor'd, and of equal Worth, tho' not the very ſelf ſame, is what implies the Latin <hi>Mutare.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Between theſe two <hi>Lendings,</hi> this di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity intercedes. In the <hi>Firſt;</hi> the Lend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er diſpoſes only of the Uſe, of what he lends, not to be conſum'd. In the <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond,</hi> Uſe being inſeparable from Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption, the Lender grants both Uſe and Conſumption of the thing. The Firſt grounds an Action to the thing Lnet. The Second grounds an Action to as much, and as good in the ſame kind. As to the Firſt, What may be <hi>Lent,</hi> may be <hi>Lett,</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Mony, or Goods, which periſh in the Uſe may be Lett? ſhall be diſcuſs'd. <hi>Plautus</hi> applies <hi>Locare,</hi> to let, Mony, and <hi>place</hi> ones Mony, is the Common Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion.</p>
               <p>But before I Proceed to examine this Point, I ſhall lay down ſome Truth, very matterial, to the main? Truth I think not to be ſhaken, as being rooted in the very Definition of Uſury.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:39313:14"/>
               <head>CHAP. IV. <hi>Poſitions drawn from the Definition of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RY.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>FIrſt. <hi>Gain, upon any Account, but Lending, is no <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury.</hi> The Proof. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury</hi> is a Gain, for a thing <hi>Lent</hi> as <hi>Lent.</hi> But <hi>Gain</hi> upon any account, but that of <hi>Lending,</hi> is no Gain for a Thing <hi>lent</hi> as <hi>lent,</hi> therefore no <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury is a Sin against the Law of Nature.</hi> Thus S. <hi>Thomas,</hi> with the reſt of Divines. The Proof. A Lend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er by giving the Uſe of what he Lends, makes the ſaid Uſe no more his own, but to exact Payment, for what's no more ones own, is an Injuſtice, viſible by the Law of Nature; therefore to receive Payment of what's Lent, <hi>as Lent,</hi> in which <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury</hi> conſiſts is againſt the Law of Nature; and therefore, as Such, 'tis reduced to Stealth, forbidden in the Seventh Commandment.</p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:39313:15"/>
               <p>Thirdly. <hi>Not only Extortion, or Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>action upon the Poor, is <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury.</hi> The Proof; Increaſe for Mony <hi>Lent, as Lent</hi> may be required of the Rich, and this is Uſury; but in this no Opreſſion of the Poor; therefore Uſury conſiſts not only in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acting upon the Poor, as our two Knights hold, and the Author of the Letter im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugned by <hi>Du Tertre,</hi> ſeem to affirm.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, <hi>Whatever is not reducible to Stealth, and againſt the Law of Nature, can be no <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury.</hi> This is but a ſequel of the ſecond Aſſertion. The Proof. If all Uſury he reducible to Stealth, and againſt the Law of Nature, nothing can be U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury, which is not againſt the ſame Law, otherwiſe this Contradiction would en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue, That all Uſury is againſt the Law of Nature, and that ſome Uſury is not; now to make nearer our Caſe.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, <hi>A Joint-Agreement in a Body Politick, for the Putting out of Mony at <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe, cannot be against the Law of Nature.</hi> Proof. Such an Agreement would render it no more Stealth, or Injurious to any. <hi>Volenti non fit injuria.</hi> It would accord with the firſt Rule of Equity; <hi>Do as you would be done by;</hi> It cannot therefore oppoſe
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:39313:15"/>the Law of Nature, being ſo conform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to it.</p>
               <p>Concluſion. <hi>The ſaid Agreement paſſed into Cuſtom, or Law, for the taking Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt for Mony put out, makes it to be no <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury.</hi> The Proof. It makes it neither to be Stealth, nor againſt the Law of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, but what's not againſt the Law of Nature, or Stealth, is no Uſury; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it makes it no Uſury.</p>
               <p>If in rhe Proof of any of theſe Truths, Fallacy impoſes upon me, I ſhall be grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to the Diſcoverer. I am no ſtranger to the Vertue of Law, as to Temporal Concerns; it is not only Lawful, but Conſcience, to ſubmit ones private Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the Publick. Law regulates all Contracts as to <hi>Meum</hi> and <hi>Tuum,</hi> in ſo much as Property or <hi>Domaine,</hi> by Divines, as well as Lawyers, is defin'd with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to Law. <hi>Property,</hi> they ſay, <hi>Is a Right in a thing, extending its ſelf to all <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſes, and Diſpoſitions of the ſaid thing, not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden by Law.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>One may Object. It is not in the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of any Legiſlative Authority, to make Uſury no Uſury, or Stealth no more Stealth, and to take Intereſt for Mony
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:39313:16"/>Put out, is both Stealth, and Uſury.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Though it be not within the Verge of Human Juriſdiction, to make Uſury, no Uſury, or Stealth, no more Stealth; yet it lies in the compaſs of that Power, and even of a Particular's Power, to prevent from being Uſury, or Stealth, what otherwiſe would be ſo, not by altering the Law of God, and Nature, againſt Stealing and Uſury, but by a voluntary Change, or Abatement of Property and Right. For Example. One beſtows a Parcel of Ground to be a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, for the Poor. Had the Poor turn'd in their Goods, before its being made Common, they had been guilty of Treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs, and Stealth, which they incurr not, after the Right of Common granted them. The Caſe, if I miſtake not, is ours: If a Perſon will freely give Five <hi>per Cent.</hi> and Security for the Principal, you may take it, as his Gift, ſtanding good in Law, without Uſury. This is what the Nation agrees to, including each Particular's Conſent; Perhaps, in Recompenſe of the Good, accruing to the general Eaſe, and publick Profit; and Perchance, by way of Penalty, for
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:39313:16"/>Prodigals and Spendals; ſo that what excluding this general Conſent and Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, might have been Uſury in Vertue of the ſaid Agreement, ceaſes to be ſuch, For he that takes 5 <hi>per Cent.</hi> takes it as granted by Law and Cuſtom, for Mony Put out; and not as Covenanted by himſelf, for <hi>Mony</hi> as <hi>Lent,</hi> Cuſtom be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Previous to the Putting out of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and including a general Concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, which makes the Intereſt allow'd ſpontaneous, and freely given.</p>
               <p>Nor doth this Procedure intrench up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on any, but equally Provides for all, ſince as a Perſon putting out Mony, muſt Receive, ſo taking up, he pays as much. And it often happens, that the ſame Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, who has Mony out, is forc'd to take up, Suppoſe then he pay as much as he receives, Where is the Gain? This Diſcourſe, not manag'd, as I find by others, I think fit to Promote by the following Enquiry.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:39313:17"/>
               <head>CHAP. V. <hi>Whether the Law of the Land render the taking</hi> 5 per Cent. <hi>ſafe in Conſcience?</hi>
               </head>
               <p>EXception may be made againſt the Queſtion, as grounded on a falſe Suppoſition, and that we have no Poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Law for the Putting out Mony at Uſe, but that it is purely Permiſſive; That Law may even permit Uſury, to avoid greater Evils, as Divines affirm, yet not Juſtifie it, as to Conſcience.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> That we have no Poſitive Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute Law, which as Sir <hi>Robert Filmer,</hi> pag. 92. informs us, varies as to the Caſe, it matters not; for 'tis enough we have Law. But we have even Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute-Law; for the Statutes againſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt for Loan, may be underſtood of Intereſt for pure Lending; and not only may, but muſt be ſo interpreted, all Gain <hi>not purely for Lending,</hi> being no U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:39313:17"/>as has been made out from its Definition. Much more ſince the <hi>Conſtant Practice,</hi> as the ſame Sir <hi>Robert</hi> tells us, <hi>of the Common Law of this Land, and alſo Chancery in Point of Equity, doth not only allow Intereſt, where there is a Contract for it, but alſo gives it where there is none<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> What better Interpreter of Statute-Law, than Common Law and Equity?</p>
               <p>This Practice becomes Law, according to the Deciſion. L. <hi>De quibus</hi> 32. ff. <hi>de Legibus. Inveterata conſuetudo, pro Lege non immerito Cuſtoditur.</hi> An antient Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom is deſervedly held for Law, and <hi>Lege</hi> 35. <hi>de Legibus ſed &amp; ea quae longa con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuetudine approbata ſunt, &amp; per annos pluri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mos obſervata, velut tacita civium Conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio, non minus, quam ea quae ſcripta ſunt ſervantur.</hi> But alſo thoſe things, which are approved by long Cuſtom, and have been obſerved for many Years, as a tacit Convention of the People, are no leſs to be obſerved than Written Laws. <hi>Quid enim intereſt</hi> L. 72. ff. <hi>de Legibus. An ſuffragiis Populus ſuam voluntatem declaret, an Rebus ipſis, &amp; Factis.</hi> For what imports it, whether the People de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare their Wills by Suffrages or Deeds?</p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:39313:18"/>
               <p>True it is, Where the Legiſlative Power lodges not in the People alone, as it doth not with us, the Kings Tacit conſent, is a requiſit, and in our Caſe we have it more than Tacit, ſince the Courts which all act in his Name, adjudge Intereſt to be pay'd; Now if practiſe is not only the beſt Interpreter of written Law, but kept up for the ſpace of ſome years, even preſcribes againſt Law, and its ſelf often becomes Law, who can except juſtly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Queſtion made, as being upon a falſe Suppoſal?</p>
               <p>Neither can our Law be ſaid, to be meerly Permiſſive, for a Permiſſive Law, grants no Action to an Uſurer againſt the Borrower. But our Judges, Poſitive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly uphold the Creditor, as to a Right he has by Law, to receive Intereſt; The Law then muſt allow of that Right, Judges being Oblig'd, to decide according to Law; Whence the Law appears to be Poſitive, and not purely Permiſſive; for were it meerly Permiſſive, it could give no Right, as is clear, to take Intereſt, but only wink at it, whereas our Law, grants Procuration Mony, to ſuch, who makes it their Buſineſs, to find, and Put out
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:39313:18"/>Mony for others. And is not this Poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively to cooperate by the encouragement of Reward? The Law of the Nation then is clearly Poſitive, for the Putting out Mony at Uſe.</p>
               <p>This Poſitive Law, I hold to be a plain Juſtification of the Practice, even as to Conſcience; It being to be Preſumed, in favour of the Law, that it would not Poſitively concur to what were unjuſt, were Uſury; were againſt the Law of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and God. This Preſumption ought to ſtand good, until ſuch time as the ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity of the Law be Evidenc'd, which has not yet been done.</p>
               <p>To queſtin its Juſtice, betrays an Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance of what force Law is. It even overrules and debars Natural Right, of Particulars, as in the Caſes of Preſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Laſt Wills, and Minors, who tho' true Maſters of their Eſtates according to the Apoſtles <hi>Cum ſit Dominus omnium,</hi> are hindred by Law to diſpoſe of them. What more Sacred and Binding than an Oath? Yet by the Law both of <hi>Caſtile,</hi> and <hi>Portugal,</hi> all <hi>Obligations, Contracts</hi> and <hi>Conventions,</hi> appertaining to the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral Court, if Sworn to, are made Void in
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:39313:19"/>Law, to the end Cauſes appertaining to the Temporal, in vertue of an Oath, may not devolve to the Spiritual Court, to the Prejudice and limitation of the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral Juriſdiction; ſo the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> to ſay nothing of Clandeſtine Marriages, (<hi>Seſſ.</hi> 25. c. 16. <hi>de Reg.</hi>) Annuls even an Oath of <hi>Renounciation,</hi> made two Months before Profeſſion. Evidence, of what force Law is, in Caſes much harder than ours, in which, all Parties making up the Legiſlative Power agree, as to a certain Rate, for Mony to be Put out, as Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable to the Publick, and a fit means to prevent thoſe Strifes and debates, which might ariſe from the Titles, Divines ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally allow of, for the taking Intereſt, <hi>viz. Emergent Damage, Lucre ceaſing, and Danger of Principal,</hi> which often vary, and are now more, now leſs.</p>
               <p>Our Law then, ſtands upon good grounds, and makes good the ground its ſtands on; It being a Tenent amongſt Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines, that Law takes away doubt, it being in Poſſeſion of Command, Nay tho' proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Reaſon, but not evident, appear a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt its uprightneſs, it ſtill keeps its Poſt. (<hi>Suares de Legibus</hi> lib. 1.) Other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:39313:19"/>there being few Laws, againſt which ſome objection might not be ſtar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, too much licenſe in queſtioning them, would encourage to <hi>Non-Compliance</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So that in Anſwer to the Queſtion, my Opinion is, ever vailing to better Reaſon, that more Conſcience, ought to be made of condemning the Putting out Mony, as Authoriz'd by Law, than of Practiſing it. For were its Lawfulneſs doubtful, and not in ſo high a degree Probable, if not Evident; as both Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and Authority renders it, ſtill Poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion ſtands for Law. Wherefore Divines hold it no wiſe requiſit, That he that Puts out Mony, either know the grounds of the Law, or expreſs the ways or Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles juſtifying it. But it ſuffices, he intend to do what is Juſt, and no ways Offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive to God; As in Prudence he may judge to be what Law, and conſtant Practiſe ſtand for.</p>
               <p>This is the Deciſion of <hi>Bartolus.</hi> L. <hi>Quis fugitivus §. apud Leonem de Aeadil. Edict.</hi> of <hi>Navarrus, Binsfield,</hi> and <hi>Tira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quellius,</hi> viz. <hi>That a Contract in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe, with Learned Men, of known Integrity, though in Law ſomewhat dubious, obſcure, and
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:39313:20"/>moving ſome apprehenſion of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury, is not to be judg'd <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurious;</hi> What would they have ſaid to the Caſe, manifeſtly upheld by Law and Practice? I cloſe this Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragraph with this Syllogiſm of S. <hi>Tho. quod l.</hi> 9. <hi>Art</hi> 15. which may ſerve as a Rule in this, and the like Caſes. <hi>Illud quod ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>git in Commune Periculum, non eſt ab Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia ſuſtinendum, ſed Eccleſia ſuſtinet, ergo non eſt poriculum Peccati Mortalis.</hi> That which inclines to a Common danger, is not to be born with by the Church, but the Church bears with it, therefore no danger of Mortal Sin. Therefore no <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:39313:20"/>
               <head>CHAP. VI. <hi>Whether Mony be Capable of being LETT.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe Deciſion of this Queſtion alone, might put an End to the preſent Controverſy; for if Mony can be Lett as other Moveables, or Immoveables are, like Intereſt may be receiv'd, it being for <hi>Letting,</hi> and not for <hi>Lending.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That Mony is not capable of <hi>Letting,</hi> is commonly diſcourſed thus: <hi>Location</hi> or <hi>Letting, is a Contract by which a Perſon's Goods or Tenements are granted for Wages or Rent:</hi> So that what belongs to the Hirer, is the bare Uſe of what he pays for, the thing Lett ſtill appertaining to him, who Letts it. But Mony is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum'd in the Uſe, How then can it be Lett to Uſe, which makes it away?</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:39313:21"/>
                  <hi>My Aſſertion is, That MONY may be LETT.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That it may be Lett to other uſes, than Spending, as for a Show, tending to Preſervation of Credit; and not to Cheat, as Sir <hi>Robert</hi> flurts at Catholich Divines, or to be a Pledge, is owned by St! <hi>Tho. 2da 2dae,</hi> and by the Schools in general, but denied by him, in order to Spending; By reaſon he ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes, that Property of things conſum'd in the Uſe, is not diſtinct from the Uſe of them, ſo that who has the Uſe, has Property of them too. The Hirer then having the Uſe, has both; and therefore, is no more a Hirer, but a Proprietor, for the Time he has the Uſe, ſo that Paying Conſideration for it, He'll Pay for what is his own, and the Lender receive Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt for what belongs to the Borrower; and in this he places the Sin of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What the Holy Doctor ſuppoſes of the indiſtinction of Property and Uſe, in things conſumptible, ſince his time, has not only been queſtion'd, but the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſit goes for the more current among
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:39313:21"/>Divines, approv'd by no leſs then five Popes, witneſs <hi>Leſſius (De Juſt.</hi> lib. 2. c. 3. <hi>Dub</hi> 8. n. 38.) in this. (the now more probable opinion.) I ſee no greater diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty in letting Mony, than Letting a Horſe, for the Hirer pays only for the Uſe, the Property ſtill remaining to the Letter.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But the Property of what; Since Mony in the uſe Periſhes, to him that lays it out?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> That is to ſay, Mony is in the time 'tis us'd, and no longer, and for that time the Owner letts it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But that's almoſt Momentary.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Be it never ſo ſhort, 'tis preferable, or at leaſt, <hi>equivalent</hi> to the longer uſe of a Horſe, or Houſe. This holds, ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the ſame Phyſical and Individual Mony, which in its uſes Periſhes not in it ſelf, but to its Hirer. Yet Morally it ſtill remains, in the right the Creditor has to as much, it remains in the Security for its Reimburſment, it may alſo remain in the effects of uſing it, redounding to the Hirers Profit. So that the Letter retains the Property, tho' not the Poſſeſſion, of as much as the Hirer ows, and according to Law, may diſpoſe of it by Gift or Sale.</p>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:39313:22"/>
               <p>To the confirming what has been ſaid, upon due Reflection you'l diſcover, little or no difference, between the Letting Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny or a Horſe. A Horſe is let to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor'd the ſame, not abſolutely, but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditionally, for if by the Hirers fault it dies, he's only oblig'd, to make amends, to its full Worth. And tho' the ſame be not return'd, yet it cannot be deny'd that it was Lett. The like happens in Putting out Mony; the Letter retains a Right either to the ſame, or as much; for the Nature and Intention of Hirage, is to have a Horſe proper for the Turn; the being This, or that, is wholly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different; by reaſon it is the Species, or Quality, which render things Valuable and Serviceable for Hirage, and not the individuality.</p>
               <p>In like manner the Letter being inſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of having back a Horſe, in all reſpects as good as his own, ought to content himſelf as well, as with the Right he has to his own. And what if one ſhould Lett a Horſe, Conditioning to have as good, if not his own back; I inquire, whether this would not be a true Letting? Certainly it would. Why may not one
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:39313:22"/>ther, in the ſame manner Put out Mony? For the Letter keeps a Right to have his Summ back, and one 20 <hi>l.</hi> in Moral eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, is the ſame with another 20. So that the Summ remains ſtill the Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditor's to be reſtored, as a Horſe to the Lettor.</p>
               <p>This ſeems to have been acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Learned <hi>Cajetan, Verbo <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſura exterior</hi> §. Nov. fol. 578. <hi>Nota</hi> 2<hi>do quod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quia Lucrum <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurarium eſt ex mutuo, ideo ſiquis non mutuat ſed accommodat ſeu locat, aut Vendit Pecuniam cum pacto re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipendi aliquid Plus, non eſt <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſure, ſed lici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti ſunt hujuſmodi contractuſque dum modo Pacta fint moderata juxta qualitatem Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poris.</hi> Since Uſurious Gain is for <hi>Lending,</hi> therefore if a Perſon doth not Lend, but Lett, or Sells Mony, Bargaining for ſomewhat more, it is no Uſury, but ſuch Contracts are lawful, ſo they be moderate, according to the quality of Times. Now our Law has ſtruck up a Bargain for all, to the eaſing each Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars of that Trouble; It hath alſo Provided againſt all immoderate Gain, aſſigning a Set Intereſt now more, and now leſs, Proportion'd to the Condition
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:39313:23"/>of Times, to the excluſion of all Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, and Extortions. and thus the Law renders the Putting out Mony, no Lending, and the Intereſt allow'd, no Uſury.</p>
               <p>Whereby the way, I take notice of a Conſtruction in Common Law, which Sir <hi>Robert</hi> teaches us, of the Word <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tortion</hi> and <hi>Exaction.</hi> They are thus Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed, ſays He: <hi>Extortion is a Wrong, in taking more than is due. Exaction is the tak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of what is not due at all.</hi> This diſtinction, had it come from a School Divine, would ſcarce have eſcaped Sir <hi>Robert</hi>'s Cenſure, he's ſo ſevere upon them; for my part, I ſhould conceive, <hi>that the more that is due, is not due at all;</hi> He then who takes more than is due, in that more he takes, takes what's not due at all; and ſo <hi>Extortion</hi> in Subſtance, falls in with <hi>Exaction.</hi> The Digreſſion may ſerve at leaſt, for the Promiſcuous uſe, with Sir <hi>Robert</hi>'s leave, of the Words <hi>Extortion</hi> and <hi>Exaction</hi> whithout Cavil, upon a Nicety ſcarce worth the Laws Notice.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:39313:23"/>
               <head>CHAP. VII. <hi>Of the Obligation of Lending.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>ON what has been ſaid in the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceding Chapter, an enquiry attends by Courſe, concerning the Obligation of Lending, it being Manifeſt, that where the Obligation of giving or lending Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ceaſes, it may be Lett. To Aſſigne the bounds of this Obligation.</p>
               <p>Firſt. I reduce Dealings relating to Exchange of Property, either to Dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or Sale, in Contracts reducible to Buying and Selling, a juſt Profit is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd of, Acts appertaining to Dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as ſuch admit of no Gain, by way of Juſtice; for ſuch a Gain were Uſury in taking Intereſt, for what Donation, has made no more ones Own.</p>
               <p>Now <hi>Lending,</hi> is as ſort of Giving, as <hi>Letting,</hi> is of Selling, and one, and the ſame thing, may be <hi>Lett</hi> or <hi>Lent,</hi> or <hi>Given; Giving</hi> makes the Thing no more the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors, <hi>Lending</hi> makes a Thing, or at leaſt,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:39313:24"/>the uſe of a Thing, no more the Lender's. For the ſpace of the time tis Lent, ſo that, to require Payment for what is given or <hi>Lent,</hi> as being another's, is Palpable In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice, and Uſury, as has already been declar'd. In <hi>Letting,</hi> one Sells the uſe of what he Letts.</p>
               <p>I Secondly Reflect, that as no man is Oblig'd to Prejudice himſelf, ſo where Self-prejudice Intrudes not it ſelf, the Law of Nature Obliges one Man to help a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, the Preſervation of each, having a Reference to the Whole; and in this Caſe ariſes an Obligation, of Supplying our Neighbours.</p>
               <p>Thirdly. In extreme Neceſſity, no place for <hi>Lending.</hi> The Neceſſitous hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Natural Right, to take what may relieve their preſent Want, all things in that occaſion becoming Common, and to Refuſe a Perſon, in extreme Neceſſity, is a ſort of Theft, in retaining from him, what Neceſſity makes to be his own, and no leſs Folly, in pretending to Lend, what in extreme Neceſſity is more another's, then yours.</p>
               <p>Fourthly. In Caſes of great, tho' leſs urgent Neceſſity, than Extreme; the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:39313:24"/>Wealthy are bound, under Mortal ſin, to Succour the Poor, out of what they have Superfluous; in ordinary Neceſſities, they'r Oblig'd under Venial; Yet in thoſe Caſes, if <hi>Letting</hi> or <hi>Lending,</hi> will ſuffice their occaſions, all Obligation of giving ceaſes: This is generally the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Divines.</p>
               <p>Hence this Concluſion follows. <hi>The Obligation of Lending is Conditional. Thus to be expreſs'd. If a Perſon, will not by gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, by Selling, or Letting; cannot relieve his poor Neighbour, by the Law of Nature, He's bound to Lend out of what He abounds with.</hi> And in that Caſe to exact Intereſt, is Uſury unjuſtifiable, by any Law what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever. The ſaying of St. <hi>Baſil</hi> being moſt true, upon the Text of the 14 <hi>Pſal. Qui Pecuniam ſuam non dedit ad <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſuram.</hi> He that hath not given his Mony to U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury. <hi>Enim vero inhumanitas eſt maxima, Si is qui egeſtate premitur, mutuum ad Vitae Subſidium qui erat; Dans vero minime contentus, ex Miſeri calamitate Provertus &amp; opes excogitet. For certainly, ſays the Saint: It is the greateſt inhumanity, whilſt one Borrows a Subſidy for life, the Lender not content with the Principal, Deviſes In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:39313:25"/>and Riches, out of the Calamity, of one in Miſery.</hi> In this Paſſage you have, in what, according to the Senſe of St. <hi>Baſil, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury conſiſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In other Caſes, containing no Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Lending, Mony may be Lett, or Put out, as Law and Cuſtom allows. Since the Obligation of Lending, gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally ſpeaking, extends no farther, than to ſmall Sums, ſufficient to Relieve Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Neceſſity. Yet in caſe a Perſon free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Lends never ſo great a Sum, the Law cannot allow him Conſideration for it; for This were Uſury, as hath been more than once repeated, and Prov'd, forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den by the Law of Nature, and God; to which Inferior Laws, to be Laws, muſt Conform.</p>
               <p>Having prov'd what Occurr'd unto me, not ſo expreſly Treated of in Schools, towards the making out the Lawfulneſs of taking Intereſt, for Mony Put out; 'tis time I ſhould produce, the Common Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles, Aſſign'd by Divines, for the Juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:39313:25"/>
               <head>CHAP. VIII. <hi>The Common Title aſſign'd by, DIVINES.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>COnſidering the Nature of Things, which may be Lett, I find in none, ſo many, and ſo good Titles, for juſt Gain, as in the Letting of Mony. A Houſe for Inſtance, ſtands Empty, of no Profit, or preſent uſe, to the Owner, apt to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay, for want of Inhabiting; yet it may be Lett, and Rent received for it. Upon what Score? For the living in it? But that kept it in Repair; And is it Juſt, the Inhabitant ſhould pay for what he betters? It may be ſaid, it is the Tenant's Conveniency, which deſerves the Rent. The ſame with greater Reaſon, may it not be ſaid of Mony?</p>
               <p>But beſides the Hirers Convenience, the inconveniencies which attend the Lettor, are yet more Conſiderable, by Reaſon, Mony being the Price of Things, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingencies Daily, Produce occaſions of
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:39313:26"/>Lucre, and the want of it, unforeſeen Damage. The depriving oneſelf of the Profit, which probably might be made, and the Danger of undergoing Prejudices, are rateable, worth Recompence, and may be Bargain'd for, Reaſon dictating as Juſt, to provide for Self indemnity. For which Cauſe, as I ſuppoſe the Mony taken upon thoſe Accounts, is named <hi>Intereſt;</hi> as behoving each one, to require it as Due.</p>
               <p>One may interpoſe: Theſe Titles have no Place in ſuch as Hoard and Keep Mony idle in their Coffers.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> An inconſiderate Objection. Whilſt the Mony lies in Coffers, the Difficulty may be ſhut up with it. But every one hath Right to open his Coffers and to make Uſe of his Mony, to his beſt Advantage; and this Right by Putting it out, he makes it over to another. Beſides in good <hi>Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophy,</hi> Mony being a pure <hi>Medium,</hi> it is not coveted and lov'd for its own ſake, but for the Service it may be put to; as ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantageous Purchaſes, Traffick, and the like, in order to Profit; and in Caſes of Suits, Sickneſſes, impriſonments, and other too frequent Accidents, in order to prevent the harm, the Want of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:39313:26"/>in like Misfortunes, would Occaſion; of theſe Services he that puts out Mony, deprives himſelf, and that Deprivation deſerves to be conſider'd. Upon this ground runs the Deciſion of S. <hi>Thomas, Opuſc. de <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſuris,</hi> where treating of ſuch as ſell dearer, becauſe upon Truſt, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firms 'tis Uſury. <hi>Si tantum propter ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectationem ſolutionis fiat;</hi> That is, if it be for meer forbearance, but if it be to keep himſelf harmleſs, that it neither may be Uſury nor Injuſtice. But grant that neither Ceſſation of Profit, nor E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mergent Damage, be in the Caſe.</p>
               <p>Still the <hi>Hazard of Principal</hi> is Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant and great. What a multiplicity of falſe Dealers? Caſualties fruſtrate the beſt Intentions, Securities of ſoundeſt Appearance, prove often Litigeous, producing much Coſt, Trouble and Care; the expoſing ones ſelf to all this, Is it not eſtimable and worth its Value?</p>
               <p>It may be ſaid: All Lenders are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd to theſe Inconveniencies, for which cauſe, they being eſſentially con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nex'd with Lending, either Uſe-Mony, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſuch Titles, as being for Lending is Uſury; or thoſe Titles, taking away the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:39313:27"/>Nature of Lending, Uſury will become a meer Sound, and not a Word, as ſignify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing nothing.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> It is granted that all Lenders, are more or leſs Subject to thoſe Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniencies, but 'tis deny'd that they are Eſſential to Lending. For Lending in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes no more than the Act of <hi>Lending,</hi> the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> of what's Lent, and <hi>futurity</hi> of Repayment; theſe poſſibly may conſiſt without loſs of Gain, adventitious Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, or Hazard of Principal, as a Lend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er preſumes they will, and ventures it. So that he retains no Title for Intereſt; This an Uſurer heeds not, but blinded by Avarice, even in that Caſe will have Profit, with the Principal. A lender then, tho' he be expos'd to Loſs, it is becauſe he will lend, be it for Motives of Charity, ſo commended in Holy Writ, and he is to expect his Intereſt from God; or be it out of Friendſhip, and he's repaid by his own Judgment, that it becomes him ſo to do. But it were a bad illution to ſay: he could not Bargain upon the ſcore of thoſe Dangers, and ſo doing, he had been no more a Lender, and therefore no Uſurer.</p>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:39313:27"/>
               <p>The Inference which was added, that Uſury will become a meer Sound, and not ſo much as a ſignificant Term, ends in Air, and is of no Subſtance. Sir <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger Twiſden,</hi> and ſome others, make U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury a pure Invention of Churchmen, to bring more Griſt to their Mills, which were it true, they would not ſtudy to bring it to nothing, as the Objection Pretends. But Divines according to Duty, diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh no Uſury from Uſury. To exact Intereſt for what was freely Lent ſtill remains Uſury, independently of all Churchmen and Canons. To Lett where oblig'd to Lend, is Uſury; taking above what Law allows, is Uſury, at leaſt Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptive; Continuation Mony, too much in Practice, if ſome new Conſideration ariſe not, I hold to be Rank Uſury, as receiv'd Purely for <hi>Lending;</hi> all other Titles, being ſatisfied with the Intereſt, Taxed by Law.</p>
               <p>Some not over-vers'd in theſe Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, may require what I mean by Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuation-Mony?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> I mean too frequent a Practice of Uſurers, their Cuſtom is ever to have Mony at hand, to Supply ſuch as
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:39313:28"/>ſhall Addreſs unto them, <hi>First,</hi> They re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire ſo much for Procuring the Mony, then they Prefix a Set Time, for which they Lett it. <hi>Finally,</hi> The Term expir'd, they Demand what they think fit, for Continuing it in the Borrower's Hands This Laſt I ſtile Continuation Mony, and hold to be plain <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Againſt theſe Titles from the Name of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury, Du Tertre</hi> diſcourſes it after this Manner. A name is taken from the Nature of the Thing 'tis plac'd for, but the Name which is given to <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury,</hi> is for taking Increaſe, for the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> of <hi>Mony;</hi> therefore <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury</hi> conſiſts preciſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in taking the ſaid Intereſt. He pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motes it thus: General <hi>Idea</hi>'s imprinted in the Minds of all Men, cannot be falſe but <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury</hi> in the <hi>Idea</hi> of Scripture, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, Philoſophers, imports Intereſt for the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> of <hi>Mony,</hi> without Exception of emergent Damage, loſs of Gain, or danger of Principle; To receive Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt therefore for the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> of Mony, even with thoſe Exceptions, is <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> I paſs by the Major of his firſt Syllogiſm, tho' it be falſe, that Names be taken from the Nature of things, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:39313:28"/>the Names given by <hi>Adam;</hi> for the ſame thing in different Languages, is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs'd by different Names, made ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficant by the Will of Men. The Minor is deny'd; for one that buys Cheap, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives Intereſt for the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> of his Mony, and yet incurs no guilt of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury.</hi> The Conſequence therefore is no better than the Premiſes.</p>
               <p>To the Promotion of his Argument, the Major is granted, the Minor deny'd, and ſo is the Conſequence; his Major I Reaſſume and Retort it. General Idea's, <hi>Pag.</hi> 114. Imprinted in the Minds of all Men, cannot be falſe; but it is an Idea drawn out in the Minds of all Men, by the Author of Nature, that Man may provide againſt emergent Damage, loſs of Gain, and danger of Principal, that he may ſubmit to the Agreement of his Nation, tending to the Common good, therefore its Contradictory muſt be falſe.</p>
               <p>He inſtances Uſury by all is under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, for Intereſt taken for the Uſe of Mony. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſura quae ſcilicet pro uſu Pecuniae accipitur.</hi> Uſury by Reaſon 'tis taken for the Uſe of Mony. Says the Law.</p>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:39313:29"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> In Law the word <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſura</hi> has both a good and bad Senſe; Intereſt taken for the Uſe of Mony Lent, is <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury;</hi> Intereſt for the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> of Mony upon other Accounts, is no <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury.</hi> And <hi>de Facto</hi> in his 7th <hi>Chap.</hi> He juſtifies ſeveral Caſes, in which Intereſt is taken for the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> of Mony. It was a piece of Oſcitation in him, not to take Notice of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury,</hi> as ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs'd in other Languages; the <hi>Greek,</hi> the <hi>Hebrew,</hi> and <hi>Chaldaick,</hi> import more than Pure Intereſt for the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> of Mony, and could not be derived from the Latin <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But beſides the aforeſaid Titles;</p>
               <p>This other way, Divines propoſe for the Juſtice of Putting out Mony. One may purchaſe a Penſion, or Rent Charge affecting ſome Land; or Tenement, and it is ſtiled <hi>Real,</hi> or affecting only the Perſon, and 'tis nam'd <hi>Perſonal.</hi> The Contract is ſo to be drawn up, that by Repayment of the Principal, the Obligation of giving the Penſion, be clear'd; or upon Releaſing the Penſion, the Principal reſtor'd, both Parties Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venanting for Performance. As to the <hi>Real,</hi> 'tis judg'd by moſt Divines to be
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:39313:29"/>no ways <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurious,</hi> by many, and of great Credit, as to the Perſonal, Reaſon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing much the ſame for both; ſo that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding all <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>surious</hi> intentions, both Contracts are held ſafe in conſcience. Our Cuſtom then may be ſaid to involve a general Covenant of this Nature.</p>
               <p>Whatever Statute therefore has been Enacted, againſt taking Intereſt for Loan, can only be in force, in Caſes of unlawful Gain; and we are beholden to Divines, for finding out juſt ways of at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining to a Profit, which could not be made by <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury,</hi> without ſin. This is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuouſly confeſs'd by Sir <hi>Robert Filmer,</hi> tho' no Friend to Catholick Divines. But Reaſon, is ever Reaſon, come it from who it will. His words are <hi>Pag.</hi> 124. <hi>It is no Sin to avoid a Statute by Lawful means: If the Contract of Bargain, and Sale be in it ſelf Lawful, why ſhould it be a Vice, and not a Vertue, thereby to avoid the Penalty of the Law, ſince Laws are properly made, to force Men to avoid them, by Lawful means?</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:39313:30"/>
               <head>CHAP. IX. <hi>Whether in ſome Caſe, it ſtand with Law, and Conſcience, to take More than Five per. CENT.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe ordinary Method of Putting out Mony, having been diſcharg'd of the Imputation of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury;</hi> a Motion may be made, whether in ſome Caſe, one may not improve his Mony, to more than the Current Intereſt? That one may do it, by way of Traffick is unqueſtionable. So that any mans of Gaining, more than Five <hi>per Cent.</hi> juſtifiable, by the ſame Reaſons, and Law, as Traffick is, cannot but be Approv'd of, even if Putting out of Mony.</p>
               <p>My Concluſion is that, <hi>in ſome Caſe, the Gain of more then Five per Cent. is Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Caſe is of a Triple Contract, taught by moſt and ableſt Divines. The firſt is a Contract of <hi>Partnerſhip.</hi> the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:39313:30"/>of <hi>Inſuring</hi> the Principal. The Third of <hi>Inſuring</hi> the Intereſt, all three Maintain'd by Law, and Practis'd upon Exchanges, which certainly they would not be, were they againſt the Law of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and Uſurious.</p>
               <p>Suppoſe then, that all Succeeding ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Expectation, by the firſt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract, each Partie's Gain in a Year, be Computed Thirty <hi>per Cent;</hi> Suppoſe by the ſecond, a Partner Inſure his Principal, by giving Ten <hi>per Cent.</hi> Suppoſe finally, that by a third, He ſeu for Ten more, the hopes he has of Gaining Twenty; for hope of Gain is Valuable, and matter of Purchaſe, as appears in the Buying the Caſt Nett. Thus Acting, the ſaid Partner, will have Right, to Ten <hi>per Cent.</hi> and the Concluſion is made good.</p>
               <p>In <hi>Sevil,</hi> as I am inform'd, no leſs than Twelve <hi>per Cent.</hi> is taken and given by Merchants, and <hi>Du Tertre</hi> acknowledges, that Merchants of the Town-houſe, of <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris,</hi> and Exchange of <hi>Lyons,</hi> pay each Term, which is Quarterly, two and a half, Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounting to Ten <hi>per Cent.</hi> in a Year. And queſtioning himſelf, what may be ſaid to it? He coldly Anſwers <hi>que pour L. ordinaire
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:39313:31"/>cet Intereſt eſt <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſuraire.</hi> That for moſt part, ſuch Intereſt is Uſurious. So that of its own Nature, it is not, for were it, of its own Nature, Uſurious, it would al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways be ſo, and not only ordinarily. But to return.</p>
               <p>Divines agree in the Lawfulneſs of the Triple Contract, ſo it be made, with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct Perſons, and not with a Partner. Some modern <hi>Rigoriſts,</hi> except againſt it when made with the ſame. Their Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is, that the Nature of the Contract of Society, is to be ſuch, that both Loſs, and Profit, be equal to all Parties. <hi>L.</hi> 1. <hi>&amp; Seq.</hi> π <hi>.&amp; leg.</hi> 1. <hi>&amp; Seq.</hi> c. <hi>pro ſocio.</hi> But the two latter Contracts excludes, partaking in the Loſs, therefore not to be made with a Partner.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> At leaſt the Point is gained, of its Lawfulneſs in ſome Caſe, of making more than Five <hi>per Cent.</hi> To the difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Contracting with the ſame Partner, Divines anſwer, That by the Law 'tis only evinc'd, that in Vertue of the ſole Contract of Society, one cannot require from a Partner, to be inſured, but that it is no ways againſt the improving the ſaid Contract, by Addition of the two others.</p>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:39313:31"/>
               <p>I add, That the Perſon ſo contracting in Law, is not the ſame, but in this Caſe, as in others, is equivalent to three, <hi>per fictionem Juris,</hi> as the Civilians term it. In the Firſt, he acts as a Partner, in the Second, as an Inſurer of the Prnci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal, in the Third, as a Purchaſer of the Hope of Gain, which the Partner Sells him; ſo that in each he acts, as a ſeveral Perſon; and why may not all this be perform'd by a Partner, as well as ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? Since Partnerſhip, rather gives him the Preference, to the Gain in Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect?</p>
               <p>Againſt this, <hi>Du Tertre</hi> urges the Bull of <hi>Sixtus Quintus</hi>'s Beginning. <hi>Deteſtabilis Avaritia,</hi> where he condemns the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracts of Society, in which the loſs of Principal remains not in him, who Puts out his Mony, but is to be reſtor'd him with Intereſt, in Caſe it Periſh in the Partner's hands, without any Profit ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cruing to him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Firſt in that Bull, ſuch Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracts only are condemned, wherein by the ſole Contract of Society, or Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants by Conſtraint involved in it, the whole Danger of Principal, without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Conſideration, is caſt upon a Fellow-Partner,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:39313:32"/>without any Contract of Inſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, freely made, and agreed to by both Parties, which <hi>Jure Communi</hi> hold good. See <hi>Bouoc. Diſp.</hi> 394. <hi>Puncto <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nico. n.</hi> 46. citing many as <hi>Molina, Salon, Nav.</hi> &amp;c. and <hi>F. Tuccius,</hi> a Man of known Sacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Learning, in his Letter to <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitolus,</hi> witneſſes plainly, that <hi>Sixtus Quintus,</hi> being ask'd concerning this Bull, anſwer'd; That he only forbid the Conventions uſually joyn'd to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract of Partnerſhip, which are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly condemn'd by Claſſical Authors, not ſuch as they thought juſt; And this <hi>Tuccius</hi> had from the <hi>Cardinals, Toletus,</hi> and <hi>Sanctorius,</hi> who were Commiſſioned to draw up that Prohibition.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> The Bull is of no force, where not receiv'd, as the ſame <hi>Bonac</hi> obſerves, nor is it Accepted in <hi>Germany, France, Sicily,</hi> or <hi>Flanders. Leſſ.</hi> lib. 2. <hi>de Juſt.</hi> cap. 23. <hi>Dub.</hi> 13. and <hi>England</hi> may be added. But whether receiv'd or no, 'tis decided by the <hi>Rota</hi> in <hi>Farinaeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us Decis,</hi> 137, and 138. And <hi>Coccius</hi> a Famous <hi>Canoniſt,</hi> Dean of the <hi>Rota,</hi> in a <hi>Rotal Decis, An.</hi> 1602. concludes ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly, That the Bull comprehends only
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:39313:32"/>ſuch Caſes, as are Uſurious <hi>Jure Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muni;</hi> which Deciſion you'll find in <hi>Cherubinus,</hi> in the Compendium of the <hi>Ballarium, Scholio primo ad Bullam</hi> 45. <hi>Sixti Quinti.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By theſe Allegations it appears, with how ſmall Conſideration, and much want of Study, <hi>Du Tertre</hi> inſiſts upon that Bull. It cannot but be very diſagreea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to Men of Senſe and Reading, to hear ſome wordy, ſhallow Preachers, and leſſer Divines, condemn theſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Methods of Palliated Uſury. Let the beſt of them uncloak it, by Proving that the Gain made in any of the ways hitherto Rehears'd, and Authoriz'd by the Publick Good; By Civilians, by Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noniſts, and Divines is purely for Lend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, in which conſiſts the Eſſence of U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury; or that they are againſt the Law of Nature.</p>
               <p>This is to be done to Evidence, for if it remains doubtful, Poſſeſſion carries it for Cuſtom-and Law. And were it not a Tyrannizing over Souls, to ſend them to Hell, more than God himſelf can do without Evidence for Uſurers? Whole Nations for Practiſing of it, to Hell;
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:39313:33"/>Divines for Teaching it, to Hell; Lawyers to Hell, for Abetting it, Judges for upholding, to Hell. But Practiſing what? Teaching what? Abetting what? Upholding what? What only they deem'd an Injury to None; a Conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency to All, ſuitable to the Law of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and no wiſe offenſive to the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty: And for this to Hell? If this be a Zeal! It is a Zeal no better than Injuſtice. What an embroilment of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences? What a confuſion of Reſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to be made by the now Living, for their Anceſtors, and for the yet Living, by themſelves, could the miſapprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a few Auſtere Fancies, without any I Say, not manifeſt, but even proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable Reaſon, ground an Obligation of believing them? Were I furniſhed with Monſieur <hi>Du Tertre</hi>'s Oratory, How would it pleaſure it ſelf, with a breath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or two, upon ſo fair a Courſe? But enough, if not too much of what's un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neceſſary, and with the three following Enquiries, I cloſe this firſt Part.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:39313:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>CHAP. X. <hi>Of the Briſtol Bargain, Pawn Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cage, and Intereſt upon Intereſt.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>FIrſt Aſſertion. <hi>The Briſtol-Bargain no <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury.</hi> The Reaſon is, That the Gain made by it, is not for Lending, but a Real Purchaſe of an Annuity, to be paid for a ſet Number of Years. And tho' the Intereſt by the Seller's Induſtry, may come to more than Five or Six <hi>per Cent.</hi> this cannot make It Uſury, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the Profit made by Selling and Buy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, which in a Year, may exceed 20. would be Uſury, to the deſtruction of Traffick.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Second Aſſertion.</hi> The <hi>Briſtol Bargain,</hi> as repreſented, is both Juſt and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable.</p>
               <p>The Bargain as propoſed to me ſome 20 Years ago, is this; Five hundred Pounds then running at Six <hi>per Cent.</hi> was given for an Annuity of T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> hundred
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:39313:34"/>Pounds to be Paid Yearly, the ſpace of Seven Years. I then thought it ſafe, in Conſcience, and ſtill do, the more that I hear, 'tis warranted by Law; For it contains the requiſit of Equality between the Price, and what's Bought, ſo that 'tis guilty of no Injuſtice; It is not purely for Lending, ſo that it is free from Uſury. 'Tis true, the Purchaſer by Putting out the hundred Pounds yearly Paid him in, upon the expiring of Seven Years, Reimburſes his Capital, and comes to Gain 330 <hi>l.</hi> and ſomewhat more, but this, without the leaſt Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of the Seller, who, I ſuppoſe, takes the Principal, in order to make a Purchaſe, or the Paying a Debt; and not able to pay in the Whole at once, is eaſed by Paying in yearly, a Hundred, and the laſt Two hundred, paid in lieu of <hi>Intereſt,</hi> falls ſhort by Ten of the Current <hi>Intereſt</hi> at Six <hi>per Cent.</hi> So that albeit the Purchaſer may Gain a hundred and Twenty Pounds, above the Current <hi>Intereſt,</hi> the Seller of the Annuity, gives leſs by <hi>Ten,</hi> and by conſequence the Bargain is commendable.</p>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:39313:34"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Third Aſſertion Pawn Brocage, not to be excus'd from <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By <hi>Pawn-Brocage.</hi> I underſtand not, the taking a Pawn for Security, of or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Intereſt, without Power, of Alienating the ſaid Pawn; But in the Aſſertion I mean the Practice, of taking more than the uſual; and that Monthly, under forfeiture of the Pawn, in Caſe of Failure. This I take to be <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury;</hi> my Reaſons are.</p>
               <p>Firſt, It is expresſly againſt <hi>Law,</hi> ſo that that the general Agreement, which juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies the Common way, of Putting out Mony, is againſt <hi>Pawn-Brocage.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, The overplus a <hi>Pawn-broker</hi> takes, other Titles being fully Recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſe'd is preſum'd to be taken purely for Lending.</p>
               <p>Thirdly. 'Tis the preſſing Necesſity of the Poorer ſort, which <hi>Pawn-brokers</hi> prey upon, Exacting no leſs, than Fifteen <hi>per Cent.</hi> and often more, to the great Oppresſion, of their Poor Brethren, which is the very Notion of Uſury, deliver'd in Scripture.</p>
               <p>Fourthly. <hi>Pawn-brokers</hi> are ſo Inſured, of their Principal, by Pawn, that the
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:39313:35"/>Title of it Danger, and Trouble in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covering it, almoſt wholly Vaniſhes. But <hi>Emergent Damage,</hi> and <hi>Ceſſation of Lucre,</hi> ſtill remain.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Grant they do, which Brokers themſelves know beſt, yet the Danger of Principal, equaling both, and ceaſing; either <hi>Pawn-brokers</hi> are bound to take, but half Intereſt, upon thoſe Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, or others may taken the Double, for the Danger of the Prinicpal; But this would be Judg'd Extortion. <hi>Pawne-bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cage</hi> therefore, can be no better.</p>
               <p>In favour of <hi>Prawn-Brocage,</hi> Preſidents are taken from the <hi>Mounts,</hi> as they are call'd of <hi>Piety,</hi> Erected in moſt <hi>Catholick Cities,</hi> and approv'd of by the <hi>See Apoſtolick,</hi> as receiving ſomething more than Current Intereſt, towards the Maintenance of Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters and other requiſits to that Pious Work.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Diſparity is great. Firſt its no good Conſequence, from Publick to Private Autority, for were it, whatever the Publick Acts, each Particular might Perſume to do, to a Confuſion of Order, and Juſtice. For example, vindicative Juſtice, as incumbent to the Publick, is
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:39313:35"/>a Vertue, yet to good Preſident, for a private Man, to Revenge himſelf, This being reſerv'd from him, as an Incompe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent judge. It doth not follow then, that <hi>Pawn-brocage</hi> Practis'd by thoſe <hi>Mounts,</hi> and Adminiſtred by the Publick, may be put in uſe, by every Particular, <hi>Avarice</hi> being as dangerous a Paſſion, and as blind as Revenge.</p>
               <p>Secondly. Thoſe <hi>Mounts,</hi> are to take no more than what's preciſely Neceſſary to uphold them, for Relief of the <hi>Poor,</hi> without making the leaſt Gain to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. <hi>Pawn-brokers</hi> aim at raiſing For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, It enſues that <hi>Pawn-brokers,</hi> are an agrievance to the <hi>Poor;</hi> whereas thoſe <hi>Mounts,</hi> are an eaſe from the Dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, Treble, and more, which by <hi>Jews,</hi> and <hi>Jewiſh Brokers,</hi> would be Exacted of them; They were named <hi>Mounts</hi> from the Bulk of Mony Levied by the Prince, Magiſtrat, or Charitable Coutributions <hi>of Piety</hi> from the end they were Found<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, the Relief of the Poor.</p>
               <p>Fourthly. If after a year, which is the ſpace given to redeem the Pawn, the Pawn be Sold, Satisfaction being made
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:39313:36"/>for Principal and Intereſt, the Surplus is to be reſtored to the <hi>Borrower.</hi> How well, this is perform'd, by <hi>Pawn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brokers,</hi> let their Conſcience tell. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, according to the Law of Nature, they ought not to be their own Dealers, and take advantage from the Miſery of the Poor. For this Reaſon I apprehend <hi>Leo the</hi> 10th. with the Approbation of the <hi>Lateran Council,</hi> held by his appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, requires the Confirmation of the See <hi>Apoſtolick,</hi> to the Erecting the ſaid <hi>Mounts.</hi> On what Authority then can <hi>Pawn-brokers</hi> rely, who not only Act without it, but conſequently againſt it, and our National Laws? So that Reaſon and Authority duly conſidered, our Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertion holds.</p>
               <p>Fourth, Aſſertion <hi>Intereſt upon In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, as the words ſound declares it ſelf <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury,</hi> they importing double Intereſt, for one and the ſame Principal, which is Exaction.</p>
               <p>But the Caſe may be ſtated thus, a years Intereſt for example of Twenty Pound is due. Now in caſe of <hi>non Pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> and the Creditor demand new In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, for what's unpay'd, from the time it was due?</p>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:39313:36"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> If the Creditor at the due time, demands not his Intereſt, but voluntarily lets it run on, by way of for bearance, he can demand nothing, by reaſon the forbear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, as being of his own free Will, inveſts the Nature of a Gift, for which as ſuch, nothing can be required, and ſo to take In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, for what ſtill remains Intereſt, as never having been Converted, into a Principal, would be Uſury. But ſuppoſe the Creditor, in due time call for his Intereſt, and by Agreement, with the Debtor, in place of receiving it, Converts it into a Principal. I ſee no Uſury in it, for as he may joyn an other Sum to the former, ſo he may the Intereſt; and the Conſideration to be had for it, cannot be ſaid to be Intereſt, upon Intereſt, but up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on what was Intereſt, and is now become a Principal.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>What if the Debtor being call'd upon, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe to Pay what's due?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Caſe is the ſame. For from the time 'tis Challeng'd, the Debtor is an unjuſt detainer of what would be a Principal, in the Creditor's hands, and capable of improving; now the loſs of the ſaid Improvement, is to be made Good.</p>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:39313:37"/>
               <p>Wherefore the Civil Law diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhes Uſury of pure Gain, for Lending, and Uſury of Compenſation. The firſt is ever forbidden, the ſecond is allow'd of (L. <hi>Socium.</hi> ff. <hi>pro ſocio.</hi>) Where if a Partner defers to Pay in due time, his fellow Partner, 'tis thus decided: <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras quoquae praeſtare debet, ſed non quaſi <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras, ſed quod ſocii Intereſt, Moram eam ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibuiſſe. He muſt alſo Pay<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury, not as <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury, but becauſe it concerns a Partner, that he hſould not ſuffer by Delay, and L.</hi> Uſuras Cod. de Uſuris. <hi>Cogitur Emptor qui in Solutionis Mora eſt <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſuras inſuper ſolvere Venditori. The Buyer who defers Payment, is to Pay over and above, Intereſt to the Seller.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Notwithſtanding what has been ſaid, if we have any Peculiar Law, againſt taking Intereſt for what was Intereſt; I Think it not ſafe in Conſcience to require it. Law being a Rule of Property and conſequently juſt Gain. And there may be juſt Reaſon for the Laws for bidding it. <hi>viz.</hi> to put a Stop to the Ruin of Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies which certainly attends ſuch, as either cannot, or neglect to Pay the firſt Intereſt. For the burden, of a new Payment coming upon them, will render them leſs able to Pay the Second.</p>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:39313:37"/>
               <p>Having performed, I hope as far as Neceſſary, the firſt Part of my Task, in clearing the Putting out Mony at Uſe, from the foul Scandal of Uſury, by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fronting it with the Law of Nature, as interpreted by Divines, and Lawyers, I conclude with an Anſwer to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint of <hi>Du Tertre:</hi> That if Divers by taking up Mony, run themſelves into Poverty; others by Putting out, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit their Principal, 'tis the fault of Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars, and no want of Proviſion in the <hi>Law,</hi> which by moderating <hi>Intereſt,</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vides for the Firſt againſt <hi>Extortion;</hi> and allows to the Second, the Security they ſhall require. Caſualties ought not to be Rules, otherwiſe on the ſame Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, all Trades muſt Ceaſe, ſince a Profeſſion which is one Man's Making, is often the Undoing of another. One by taking up Mony clears his Eſtate, and prevents great Miſchiefs; or Recruits his ſinking Trade and Reputation; ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Redoubles his Debts; the Fault is not in taking up the Mony, but in the Management.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="part">
            <pb n="64" facs="tcp:39313:38"/>
            <head>PART. II. <hi>Of the Caſe as to Scripture.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XI. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RY Conſider'd as to the Old TESTAMENT.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe Reverence and Compliance due to God's Word in Holy Writ, takes Place of all Reaſons and Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties hitherto made uſe of; nor can any Human Law, or Cuſtom, tho' ſeeming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tending to the Publick Welfare be of force, in oppoſition to Divine Command. For, as <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſolidly Determins; <hi>Ad exhibitionem operis Prior est Majeſtas Divinae Poteſtatis, Prior eſt Auctoritas im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perantis, quam utilitas ſervientis.</hi> The
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:39313:38"/>Majeſty of Divine Power, the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding Authority, precedes the Utili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of him that ſerves. It is but Ration<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al therefore, that I ſhould confer what has been ſaid, with thoſe Texts of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, in which Uſury is condemn'd.</p>
               <p>To the Explaining how far they relate to our Caſe.</p>
               <p>The firſt Paſſage is, <hi>Exod.</hi> 22. <hi>v.</hi> 25. <hi>Si pecuniam mutuam</hi> &amp;c. <hi>If thou lendſt Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny to any of my people being poor, that dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth with thee, thou ſhalt not urge them, as an Exactor, nor oppreſs them with <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſuries.</hi> The Second is <hi>Levit. cap.</hi> 25. <hi>v.</hi> 35. <hi>Si attenuatus,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>If thy Brother be impover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſhed and weak of hand, and thou receiveſt him as a Stranger, and ſojourner, and he live with thee, take no <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury.</hi> And Ver. 27. <hi>Thou ſhalt not give him thy Mony to <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury, and an overplus of the Fruits, thou ſhalt not exact of him.</hi> The third is Deut. c. 23. v. 19. <hi>Non faeneraberis Fratri tuo,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Thou ſhalt not lend to thy Brother Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny to <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury, nor Corn, nor any other thing, but to a Stranger.</hi> This is whatever <hi>Moiſes</hi> has left in his Law touching Uſury.</p>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:39313:39"/>
               <p>The two firſt places are but an Expla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of the Law of Nature, both Conditional, and no abſolute Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand. The Condition is, <hi>If thou Lend,</hi> which implies not ſo much as a Precept of Lending. But that's not all; the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition requir'd to the guilt of Uſury, as the Words lie, is not meerly of Lend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, but lending <hi>to the Poor, and weak of hand, viz.</hi> not able to work; From them to take more than was Lent, is Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presſion, Prohibited under the Notion, <hi>Thou ſhalt not oppreſs them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To the Poor, little ſuffices for their preſent Wants, and to require ſole Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>payment of them, is more, than to take Intereſt for greater Sums from the Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient. The Law therefore aims not the leaſt at the Caſe we are in; for who puts out Mony <hi>to Poor and weak of hand?</hi> Few or None. And yet the Law condemns only ſuch of inhuma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity as do, by ſtiling this <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury; Neſhec, a Ravenous bite, or the bite of a Dog.</hi> A name perfectly misbecoming the Practice of Putting out Mony, Profitable to all Parties concern'd. And no wonder if <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury,</hi> as expreſs'd in Law, grounded
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:39313:39"/>ſo juſt a Deteſtation of it in holy Fathers, moving them to ſo frequent, and vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment invectives againſt it. The Plaineſs of the Expresſion in the Law, has en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courag'd ſome to fix all Uſury upon the Oppresſion of the Poor, and would in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline me to do the ſame, did not Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of Reaſon, the Light and Law of Nature, extends its Notion yet farther, to a <hi>Gain</hi> made purely for <hi>Lending.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The third place in <hi>Deuteronomy,</hi> tho' ſomewhat varying in Words, contains no more than the former. This I make out; Firſt, from the Title, Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, and ſcope of the Book. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, from the Text it ſelf.</p>
               <p>The Title of the Book given by the <hi>Rabbins,</hi> is <hi>Miſne,</hi> a Reiteration of the Law, and by the <hi>Septuagint, Deuterono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mium,</hi> Signifying a Second Law; not as different from the former, Publiſh'd on Mount <hi>Sina;</hi> but as being a Repetition of it. See <hi>Theodoret. q.</hi> 1. in <hi>Deut.</hi> S. <hi>Auſtine. q.</hi> 49. S. <hi>Athanaſius,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">In Prolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go Galeato.</note> in <hi>Synopſi.</hi> S. <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome</hi> words it thus; <hi>Deutero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomium 2da Lex, &amp; Evangelicae Legis pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>figuratio, nonne ſic habet ea quae prima ſunt,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:39313:40"/>ut tamen nova ſint omnia de Veteribus? Deuteronomy</hi> Prefiguring the Evangelical Law, hath it not the firſt things after ſuch a manner, that of Old, they ſeem new? And this by Reaſon of the Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent and ſtatelier Tone, <hi>Moiſes</hi> takes in this Book; When after 40 Years Travel, and glorious Atchievments, being upon his Departure for a better Life. He, to a new People, their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genitors being deceaſed, makes a ſecond Promulgation of the Law, but more Emphatically, to ratify the Covenant be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween God and that People. By the <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle</hi> therefore of the Book, it's Occaſion and Intent, the Law written in it, in Subſtance, varies nothing from it ſelf, given in the former.</p>
               <p>This 2dly, is made out from the Text it ſelf. For the Negative, <hi>Thou ſhalt not Lend to <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury,</hi> is no more than equivalent to the Conditional. <hi>If thou Lend, thou ſhalt not take <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury.</hi> And ſo 'tis coinci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent with the former. Whether this <hi>Law</hi> were only <hi>Judicial,</hi> as the Knights will have it, proper to the <hi>Jews,</hi> or <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral,</hi> extending it ſelf to all Mankind; I examin not, but ſuppoſing it Moral,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:39313:40"/>yet it nothing affects the Caſe of Putting out Mony, without Oppresſion, or Injury.</p>
               <p>The Law thus expounded, affords us in few words, a general and true Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction to the many and vehement Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions of the Prophets againſt <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury.</hi> For the Prophets, tho' inſpir'd to be the Preachers, and Interpreters of the Law, yet they were no Givers of a new Law; Wherefore our Saviour, <hi>Mat.</hi> 22. puts a diſtinction between the <hi>Law and the Prophets;</hi> Uſury therefore with them, muſt ſignify no more than what is written in the words of the Law. According to theſe, S. <hi>Baſil</hi> gloſſes the 5th <hi>Verſe</hi> of the 14th <hi>Pſalm.</hi> And <hi>David</hi> in the 71 <hi>Pſ-Verſe</hi> 13. by the words, <hi>He ſhall ſpare the Poor and Needy,</hi> gives us the Senſe of the following <hi>Verſ. From <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury and Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, he ſhall redeem their Souls;</hi> As <hi>Pſal.</hi> 54. he joins <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury with Guile.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Neither doth the Place in <hi>Ezek.</hi> c. 18. much Exagerated to little purpoſe by <hi>du Tertre,</hi> expreſs any thing, not Mentioned in the Law, for that <hi>more</hi> or <hi>increaſe</hi> there mention'd, and in other Places, is the ſame ſpecified in the Law, for <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury,</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden under the Proper Name of <hi>Neſhec.</hi>
                  <pb n="70" facs="tcp:39313:41"/>And the milder of <hi>Tarbith</hi> or <hi>Increaſe,</hi> given it by the <hi>Jews,</hi> as was Remark'd in the 2d. <hi>Chapter.</hi> An honeſt Increaſe, and upon juſt Conſiderations, is no where blamed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Chriſt</hi> indeed, to whom all Power was given, in Heaven and Earth, abroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Ceremonial Law, and ſome Judicial of the Old Teſtament, might have Eſtabliſhed, a Peculiar as to the preſent Cafe, But his Divine Wiſdom, left things, as to that Point in the ſtate they were; Declaring only when queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned, by a Sawcy Doctor, <hi>Matt.</hi> 22. That on Charity, <hi>the whole Law depended, and the Prophets.</hi> So that if the Putting out Mony, be no Aggrievance, by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence not againſt Charity; As to <hi>Law,</hi> and <hi>Prophets</hi> it reſts Good.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:39313:41"/>
               <head>CHAP. XII. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RY Conſider'd, as to the New TESTAMENT.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe ſingle Text, making to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Purpoſe, is <hi>Luke</hi> c. 6. <hi>v.</hi> 35. <hi>mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuum date nihil inde ſperantes. Lend, hop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing nothing thereby.</hi> This paſſage, however ſo much Inſiſted upon, gives little Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance to ſuch as are Averſe to the Put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting out Mony at uſe. Our <hi>Saviour</hi> in that <hi>Chapter</hi> Intermixing many things of Counſel, with others of Precept; Be pleas'd to peruſe it. This ſaying, Divines hold to be only of Counſel, and the Conjunction of Lending, with other Works, which are not of Precept, Is no feeble Confirmation of it. <hi>Verſe</hi> 29. 'Tis ſaid: <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto him that ſmiteth thee on the one cheek, offer alſo the other. And</hi> verſe 30. <hi>Give to every man that asketh.</hi> This lays no Obligation of Giving; no more doth the firſt of Lending.</p>
               <p>Beſides Reaſon dictates the Propoſition
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:39313:42"/>to be capable of Reſtriction; For tho' a Lender, be bound to hope no Increaſe by Lending, he may hope for a Requital of Gratitude, Friendſhip, or a like return; This indeed as being of leſs Perfection, than to hope it from God, we are Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelled to abſtain from, by hoping <hi>nothing</hi> from Man. Otherwiſe, why might not the unnam'd Contract, <hi>Do ut Des. I give to be given to,</hi> as well hold Good, being Authoris'd by <hi>Chriſt</hi> in the ſame <hi>Chapter</hi> if words be taken as Writen; <hi>Give; and it ſhall be given to you?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But no need of all this. This particle <hi>thereby</hi> Moderates and reſtrains the Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative <hi>nothing;</hi> So that the words of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> as I Apprehend, contains both <hi>Counſel</hi> and <hi>Precept, Counſels</hi> in the Affarmitive part; <hi>Lend,</hi> out of the Caſe of Neceſſity; in Caſe of Neceſſity; Precept, and Prohibition in the <hi>Negative</hi> part, hop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing nothing <hi>thereby,</hi> viz. <hi>for Lending.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Three other Places, in the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, preſent themſelves. The firſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25. <hi>v.</hi> 27. in the Parable of the Talents. <hi>Thou oughtſt therefore,</hi> ſays the Lord, to the Idle Servant, <hi>to have put my Mony to the Bankers, and then at my coming, I ſhould
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:39313:42"/>have receiv'd mine own, with <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury.</hi> The ſecond is, <hi>Luke</hi> the 19. <hi>v.</hi> 23. Where the Noble Man, to the ſame Purpoſe utters himſelf. <hi>Wherefore then gav'ſt not thou my Mony into the Banks, that at my coming, I might have required mine own with <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>My intent go's no farther than to ſhew by theſe Parables, How the putting out Mony at Uſe, was Cuſtomary among the <hi>Jews;</hi> a Parable being: <hi>The applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a well known thing,</hi> as the Putting out Mony was; <hi>to aleſs known,</hi> as the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Heaven. The Parable moreo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver repreſents unto us a twofold Gain: the one of Trade, the other by Putting out Mony at Uſe. The omiſſion of this, as obvious and of leſs Trouble, as alſo leſs Profit, is reproached to the idle Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant; Uſury in that place, being taken in a good Senſe, as Interpreters obſerve. It having then been a Cuſtom of the <hi>Jews,</hi> to put out Mony, had it been Uſury ſo to do, expresſly againſt Law; Chriſt ſo Zealous in the reform of other Diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, had never paſſed ſo great an one in ſilence.</p>
               <p>The third place, <hi>Matth.</hi> the 21th, and <hi>Jo.</hi> the 2. relating the Execution done by our Saviour upon the <hi>Bankers</hi> in the
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:39313:43"/>
                  <hi>Temple,</hi> has ſcarce a ſhadow of Difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; that Comportment of his, having proceeded from the abhorrence not of Uſury, but of the <hi>Profanation</hi> of the <hi>Temple,</hi> as appears from his Words; <hi>Make not the Houſe of my Father, a Houſe of Trading.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>St. <hi>Paul</hi> in his firſt to the <hi>Corinthians, Chap.</hi> 6. in the Number of the excluded from the Kingdom of Heaven, ſpecifies <hi>Thieves</hi> and <hi>Avaricious,</hi> but makes no mention of the Putters out of Mony; the true Son of Uſury being compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended in <hi>Theft</hi> and <hi>Avarice.</hi> For Ava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rice is the Parent of Extortion, Fraud, and other unlawful Dealings, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Extortioners</hi> are nam'd there. For ſuch is the violence of <hi>Avarice,</hi> where it reigns, that it murders all thoughts of Charity, and breeds ſuch a Paſſion for Lucre, that it catches at all Means, Juſt, or Unjuſt; and one of its proper Effects, queſtionleſs is Uſury. A Diſpoſition of this Nature, conſtitutes an habitual U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurer, its Execution, and Actual.</p>
               <p>More than this is not to be cull'd out of Scripture, as to the true Conception of Uſury, ſo frequently, and ſeverely
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:39313:43"/>reprov'd by Holy Fathers; Out of whom Monſieur <hi>Du Tertre</hi> has handed the choiceſt places to me. Wherefore, my next work is, to give them their true Conſtruction, that by Miſtake, they may not work upon the Weaker.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="part">
            <head>ART. III. <hi>Of the Caſe, as to Church.</hi> TESTIMONIES of Fathers, Councils, and Popes, Anſwer'd.</head>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XIII. <hi>CITATIONS of the Latin Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AS beyond all Doubt, Holy Fathers were given to the Church for In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreters of the Divine Law, and true Senſe of Scripture; ſo the Practice of
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:39313:44"/>the Church interprets them; and is to be their final Rule, and Judge, as well as ours. Some things are ſpoken by them Orator like, others Dogmatically. Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctates of the firſt Nature, are no ways Obligatory; Sayings of the Second are yet no farther binding than the Church accepts of them. I ſay not this, that I meet with any one Quotation, that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demns the Common Practice, but only to give a true Account, how far their Authority reaches. They generally run down Uſury, <hi>viz.</hi> Either taking Intereſt for Lending, or Extortion. And he that puts out his Mony at Reaſonable Rate, cannot be ſaid to receive meerly for Lending, or to Extort.</p>
               <p>A regard alſo is to be had, to the Times and Circumſtances, in which they Writ; Mony then Running at <hi>Cent. per Cent.</hi> and Heatheniſh Cuſtoms, of Exacting upon the Poor, ſtill being in Vogue. Theſe Reaſons might influence their Zeal. and give Fire to their Vehement expreſſions; and tho' chief reſpect; is to be had, to the Primitive Doctors of the Church, yet we are not to loſe the Eſteem, due to thoſe who according to the Apoſtle, God has
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:39313:44"/>plac'd in his Church, from time to time, to Succeed them; nor ought they to be Slighted, with the Leſſening Character, of a few Caſuiſts, as <hi>du Tertre</hi> makes bold to do. The Caſuiſts, are Devines, neither a few, but the greateſt Part, and the Learnedſt, on which we ground our ſelves, as to the Caſe.</p>
               <p>The Holy Father, moſt quoted, is St. <hi>Amb.</hi> in his Book upon <hi>Tobias.</hi> The Title of his 14. Chap. is <hi>de <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſura Divina Lege Prohibita, Of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury forbidden by the Divine Law.</hi> There he thus defines. <hi>Quod cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que ſorti accedit, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſura eſt, quod velis ei no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men imponas.</hi> Whatever accrues to the Principal, is Uſury, call it as you Pleaſe; and in the following <hi>Chapter</hi> Expounding that Paſſage of <hi>Deut. Non Feneraberis Fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tri tuo ſed Alieno. Thou ſhalt not Lend Mony for <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury to thy Brother, but to the Stranger, Quis erat,</hi> ſays he; <hi>Tunc Aliene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gena, niſi Amalec, niſi Amorrhaeus, niſi Hoſtis? Ibi <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſuram exige, cui merito nocere deſideras, cui jure inferuntur Arma huic Legitime in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicantur <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſura-.-Ab hoc <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſuram exige, quem non ſit Crimen occidere.—<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi Jus belli, ibi etiam Jus <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurae. Who was then the Stranger, but Amalec, but the Amorrhaeans,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:39313:45"/>but an Enemy? From him who juſtly thou de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires to Harm, Exact <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury—Take <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury from him, who it is not a Crime to Kill— Where there is Right to War, There, then is Right to <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury.</hi> So far St <hi>Amb.</hi> after his Eloquent Manner, in a Tranſport of Zeal; For theſe words of his, contain much Matter of Diſpute; As for example; He re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrains the Word <hi>Stranger,</hi> to ſole Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, which Argues not ſo ſtrict a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe. Nor do any as I know hold it Lawful to take Uſury from an Enemy. But to Examine each Particular of the Paſſage.</p>
               <p>The Firſt, whatever accrues to the Principal is Uſury. Muſt either be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood with St. <hi>Baſil,</hi> of an Increaſe, Extorted upon the Poor, or as Divines commonly do of an Increaſe, meerly for Lending. Wherefore <hi>Lancelot,</hi> by <hi>du Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre,</hi> ſo Highly Commended. <hi>Lib.</hi> 4. of his Inſtitutions. <hi>Titulo Sept. de <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſuris.</hi> Thus defines Uſury. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſura eſt quidquid ultra ſortem mutuatam percipitur.</hi> What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever is receiv'd above the Principal <hi>Lent,</hi> is Uſury. Now that this muſt be the Mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the <hi>Saint.</hi> I Prove it from the Title of the <hi>Chap.</hi> which is of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury, &amp;c.</hi> But no
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:39313:45"/>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury</hi> but in one of thoſe two ways; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the <hi>Increaſe</hi> the <hi>Saint</hi> ſpeaks of, muſt be in one of the ſaid ways. If the Place be not thus Expounded, it fails of Truth. A free acknowledgement, made by the Borrowers, accrue to the Principal, is it U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fury? And tho' in the Banks of <hi>Rome,</hi> it be not in the power of him that Puts out his Mony, to call it in at Pleaſure; yet it lying ſafe, and the Principal remaining ſtill his, The Intereſt accrues to the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal; and will any one Preſume to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn the ſaid <hi>Mounts</hi> of Uſury?</p>
               <p>The ſecond Place; may be retorted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Alledger. The Uſury S. <hi>Amb.</hi> ſpeaks of, is Parallel'd to <hi>Killing,</hi> conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently to the greateſt Blow, to be given by an Enemy; ſuch may be heavy Extortion, and Oppreſſion of the Poor, or a Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherous Exacting Intereſt, for what was Lent; but nothing of this, in our Caſe, Suſtained by mutual Conveniency. Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the <hi>Amalecites</hi> or <hi>Amorrhaeans,</hi> had made ſome Conſttiution amongſt them, of giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Five or Six <hi>per Cent.</hi> for the Benefit of Trade, and eaſe of the Indebted, who otherwiſe, would be expoſed to much greater Damages, and for other ends tend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:39313:46"/>to the Publick Good; would the <hi>Jews,</hi> by placing Moneys in their Hands, have made a Bloody War upon them? Would they have put them to Slaughter? Would they in the leaſt have injured them? Surely no. It is violent then, to inforce thoſe ſayings upon the Caſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore us.</p>
               <p>To S. <hi>Amb.</hi> Succeeds S. <hi>Jerom,</hi> in his Commentaries on the 18 <hi>Chap.</hi> of <hi>Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiel,</hi> where having declared, That Uſury is not only for Mony, but alſo for other Conſumptible Goods; he exemplifies it in Seed time, in Corn; in which occaſion, one lends ten Buſhels, to receive 15 at Harveſt, and this by way of Charity. The Saint thus inſults their Uſurious Hypocriſy. <hi>Reſpondeat enim nobis breviter, Faenerator Miſericors; utrum habenti dederit, an non habenti? Si habenti utique dare non deberat, ſed dedit quaſi non habenti, ergo quare plus exigit, quaſi ab habente? Let the Merciful <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurer, anſwer us in ſhort, whether he gave to one, that has, or to one that has not? If to one that has, he ought not to have given it, if to him that has not, Why exacts he more from him, as from one that has?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:39313:46"/>
               <p>St. <hi>Jerom</hi>'s Ironical Challenge, given to an Uſurer, reflects not upon the Putting out Mony, as is clear. By one that <hi>has,</hi> and one that <hi>has not,</hi> he means <hi>Rich</hi> and <hi>Poor;</hi> as to Rich, no Occaſion for Lend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as to Poor, they ought not to be treated as Rich; This is the whole ſtrength of the <hi>Dilemma,</hi> which ſeems rather to allow taking Intereſt of the Rich, and not of the Poor; for could Intereſt be receiv'd from neither; How would that Inſtance hold good? <hi>Or why exacts he more from him, that has not, as if he were one that has?</hi> It alſo deſerves reflection; that the more exacted of the Poor, was no leſs than 50 <hi>per. Cent.</hi> or by ſuch <hi>as thought themſelves moſt Juſt,</hi> as the Saint ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſes it, 25. And this for Corn, which could have render'd its owner, who had it to ſpare, no more, than the Market Price; whereas Mony, is highly improv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able. Let ſome of our Country Uſurers therefore, anſwer the 2d Part. With what Conſcience, do you exact the more, for what you lend, and that only from Seed-Time, to Harveſt of 50 or 25 <hi>per. Cent.</hi> from the Poor?</p>
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:39313:47"/>
               <p>Again by the word <hi>Giving,</hi> he may mean <hi>Lending;</hi> This being a ſort of Gift, and then St. <hi>Jerom</hi> inſtances well, he ought not to have Lent, to one that has' ſince the obligation of Lending, is grounded upon our Neighbour's Neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity. And what doth this concern us? For tho' there be no Occaſion of Lend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, there may be juſt Cauſe of Put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting out Mony, and placing it with ſuch as think it but Reaſonable to pay the Lawful Intereſt.</p>
               <p>The 3d is S. <hi>Auſtine,</hi> upon the 36 <hi>Pſ. Conc.</hi> 3. He writes in this Manner. <hi>Si fae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eneraveris homini id eſt Mutuam Pecuniam dederis,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>If you lend Mony to a Man, from whom you hope to receive Increaſe, or more, than you gave him, be it Corn, Oil,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>You are an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurer, to be diſapprov'd, and not Prais'd:</hi> Mark what the Uſurer does, <hi>He will give leſs, to receive more.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A.</hi> S. <hi>Austine</hi> plainly tell us, what Uſury is, and only confirms the Common Definition; Uſury, <hi>ſays he,</hi> is a Will of giving leſs to receive more; And that you may not miſtake, what he means by <hi>Giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> it is <hi>Lending,</hi> as the Preceding words make out. <hi>If you Lend a Man,</hi> By S. <hi>Austin</hi>
                  <pb n="83" facs="tcp:39313:47"/>then is defin'd an Uſurer, who for Lending will have more, than he lent. And he who gainſays this, knows not the nature of Uſury.</p>
               <p>Theſe are the three Doctors, Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur <hi>Du Tertre,</hi> thought fit to ſelect from among the <hi>Latins,</hi> out of which a Place or two more, I have omitted for brevity ſake, as having their Anſwer in what has been ſaid.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XIV. <hi>A<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>THO RITIES of</hi> Greek <hi>Fathers, Anſwer'd.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TO the three <hi>Latins,</hi> are join'd three of the <hi>Greek</hi> Church, by <hi>Du Tertre,</hi> concluding in S. <hi>Auſtin</hi>'s words; <hi>Quomo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do Verba Scripturae intellexerunt Sancti, ſic utique intelligenda ſunt. Words of Scripture are to be underſtood, as the Saints under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood them.</hi> By Saints, S. <hi>Auſtine,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doubt means the unanimous conſent of Fathers, and not a few dubious Sentences.</p>
               <pb n="84" facs="tcp:39313:48"/>
               <p>I begin with the Author of the imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Work, <hi>Hom.</hi> 38. upon S. <hi>Matthew;</hi> Tho' cited laſt, as Arguing cloſer than the other Two. To reflect upon the Author's Guilt of Hereſie in ſome Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages, I take to be little to the Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe; but I weigh his Reaſon. He en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larges himſelf, upon the Difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Letting of Lands, and Letting of Mony. Firſt. <hi>Quoniam Pecunia, non ad aliquem <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſum diſpoſita eſt,</hi> &amp;c. Mony is not order'd to any Uſe, as a Field, but only to be the Price of Things, in Buying and Selling. Secondly, He that Hires a Piece of Land, or Houſe, has the Fruits of the Land, or Conveniency of Lodging; ſo that it is an Exchange of Gain for Gain. But if you retain your Mony, it fruits you nothing. Thirdly, Lands or Houſes decay with Uſe, Mony when 'tis Lent neither Diminiſhes, nor Deteriorates.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Authority grounded upon Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, go's no farther than the Ground it builds upon; Wherefore, anſwering Reaſon, I ſatisfy Authority. To the firſt 'tis granted, That the Uſe of Mony, and a Field, much differ. Mony of it
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:39313:48"/>ſelf produces nothing; a Field of its own Nature is fruitful; The Uſe of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, is to be the Price of things; the Uſe of a Field is not; yet in this they agree; That as a Field gives Graſs, or Corn by Tillage, ſo Mony employed in Buying, or Selling, yields Profit, and of the Right to this, he that Puts out Mony deprives himſelf. I further wiſh the Oppoſers would acquaint me with the Products of a Houſe, and other Artifici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al things, or even of Mony, when Lett out only for Show, or to be a Pledge; as on thoſe Accounts, S. <hi>Tho.</hi> allows it may be 2da. 2dae. <hi>Qu.</hi> 78.</p>
               <p>To the 2d. He that Hires Mony, has the Profit, or at leaſt the Right to Profit by it; and ſo makes an Exchange of Gain for Gain. But Mony by Keeping, affords nothing.</p>
               <p>What then ? But it would by Spending. And before Spending, doth it not enable the Owner to profit by it, as Occaſion ſerves? And is this Nothing? Hath it not more of Hardſhip, that another ſhould have the whole Gain by Laying out ones Mony, than the Onwner ſhould take part with him?</p>
               <p>To the 3d. That Houſe and Land decay
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:39313:49"/>with uſe 'tis anſwer'd, they decay more without it; and tho' Mony as to it ſelf, do not deteriorate; yet a Principal may pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh wholly to the Creditor, but Land can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not; Beſides, he that Puts out his Mony, is at leaſt depriv'd of its Uſe, in order to Gain, which is equivalent to a Decay, in Houſe, or Land; And what doth a Horſe, or Houſe yield by Keeping unlett?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Greg.</hi> of <hi>Nyſſa,</hi> in his 4th <hi>Hom.</hi> upon <hi>Eccleſiaſticus,</hi> Elegantly delivers himſelf in theſe Terms: <hi>Faenus qui aliud Latroci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium &amp; Parricidium nominaverit,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ſhall ſtile <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury a ſecond Robbery, or Murthering of a Parent, will ſay no more than becomes. For what matters it whether you break a Houſe as a Thief, to ſeize ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's Goods; or Aſſaſſinate a Man upon the Road to take what he has; or whether by Neceſſity of Paying <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe-Mony, you get what appertains not to you? God ſaid to the living Creatures, be fruitful and multiply. But the Brood of Gold, of what Matrimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny do's it come? What Mother gave it Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception?</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Who ſees not, how enormous the Uſury muſt be, againſt which, S. <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory</hi> declares, with this Eloquent Flouriſh?
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:39313:49"/>But if no Murther of Parent, no Rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bery, no Aſſaſſination, be incident to the Putting out of Mony, this cannot be the Uſury, at which he aims. A juſt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract is the Matrimony, from which the Brood of lawful Intereſt comes; publick Conveniency is its firſt Parent; whereas the Uſury againſt which he inveighs, <hi>was,</hi> (they are his Words;) <hi>Conceiv'd by Avarice, brought forth by Iniquity, Cruelty being the Midwife.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>S. <hi>Chryſoſtom. Hom.</hi> 57. upon S. <hi>Matth.</hi> appears much of the ſame mind; <hi>Quid irrationabilius quam ut ſine Agro, Pluvia, &amp; Aratro ſeminare contendas?</hi> &amp;c. <hi>What more irrational, than to Sow without Land, Rain, or Plow? I give, and grant,</hi> ſays the Uſurer, <hi>Not to have and to Hold, but to have more Return'd.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Granting it were a madneſs to Plow without Land, Rain, or Plow, as it were, to Sow in the Air; yet I am of Opininon, that neither the <hi>Saint,</hi> nor any other would deny; there are other ways of Juſt Gain, without Land, Rain, or Tillage; whereof one is, the Putting out of Mony at Uſe. In the words of the Uſurer: <hi>I give and grant, not to have and
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:39313:50"/>hold, but to have more Reſtor'd;</hi> Uſury is both expos'd, and condemn'd; for in the Terms <hi>Giving</hi> and <hi>Granting,</hi> is expreſſed an Uſurer's <hi>Lending,</hi> in order to Receive <hi>more thereby;</hi> and that <hi>more,</hi> was at the immoderate heighth of that Age.</p>
               <p>I cloſe this <hi>Chapter,</hi> Entreating only the Reader, to conſider, whether theſe, and like Allegations, are not equally a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all Princes, Exchequers, and Banks in Chriſtendom, beginning from that at <hi>Rome,</hi> which ought to be a Preſident as to Conſcience? For tho' ſuch as place their Mony in the Bank of <hi>Rome,</hi> to take away even the Shadow of meer <hi>Lend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> cannot call it in at Pleaſure, yet they may Sell the Penſion, or Intereſt they duly Receive; and ſo Reimburſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves of their Principal, and there ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver being ſcarcity of Buyers, it comes to be equivalent to the Power of Calling it in; Which being ſo, I hope <hi>Du Tertre,</hi> and his Adherents, will grant <hi>Rome</hi> to be no leſs Vers'd in Scripture, and the obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging Authority of Holy Fathers, than themſelves; and yet not ſo Preſumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, as to run, and Act in oppoſition to the ſaid Authority. It remains now to
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:39313:50"/>diſcuſs, whether it ſucceeds better with him, in his Pretenſions to Popes and Councils?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XV. <hi>Of the A<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>THORITIES of Councils.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE Quotations taken out of the Decretals, and ſome Synods, make me ſuſpect, that either <hi>Du Tertre,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood them not, or miſtook the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion. The cauſe of this my Apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion will appear, in the Examination of what he Produces.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I ſay not,</hi> ſays he, <hi>That the Council of</hi> Nice. Chap. 17. <hi>Forbad <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury to the</hi> Clergy, <hi>each one Interpreting the Place, in his own Senſe; But the Council of</hi> Carthage <hi>hath Prohibited the</hi> Clergy <hi>to Exact Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt of any Kind:</hi> c. 16. <hi>Nullus Clerico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum amplius recipiat, quam cuiquam commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daverit, Let none of the</hi> Clergy <hi>receive from any one more than he Lent.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:39313:51"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Much to the Purpoſe; to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive more than is Lent, and on the Score of Lending is Uſury, ſo that the Difinition of Uſury, has the Councils Liking. Yet what if the Council, ſhould have forbid the <hi>Clergy</hi> to Putt out Mony at Uſe, as improper to their Calling; It nothing concerns the Layety nor queſtions its Juſtice; but now it is in Practice with <hi>Clergy,</hi> as well as <hi>Layety.</hi> Wherefore Doctor <hi>Gage's</hi> Preſident of the Engliſh College at <hi>Doway,</hi> being De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by a Perſon of Quality, of the Opinion of his Community, as to the Caſe, with great Ingenuity Anſwer'd, they were Divided, for ſuch as had Mony to put out, thought it Lawful, ſuch as had none were againſt it.</p>
               <p>What he brings out of an <hi>Epiſt.</hi> of St. <hi>Leo,</hi> to the Biſhops of <hi>Campania,</hi> is much of the ſame Strain, the <hi>Pope</hi> orders puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for thoſe, <hi>who Practice <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury, and Strive to grow Rich by it. Qui uſurariam ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercent Pecuniam &amp; faenore volunt diteſcere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Had <hi>Du Tertre</hi> prov'd the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Practice Uſury; This and the Reſt, might have been Serviceable to him. But to ſuppoſe it to be Uſury without Proof,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:39313:51"/>and then to Condemn it as Prov'd is not fair, but a ſort of Juggle, to amuſe the unlearned with Quotations,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gratian</hi> is Cited in the 2d. Part of his <hi>Decretals, Cauſe</hi> the 14. q. the 3. c. 4. who out of an Ancient Council of <hi>Agde,</hi> held the 6th Century, <hi>An.</hi> 506 Defines U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſura eſt,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury is when more is Required than was given; as for example, if you give</hi> 10s. <hi>and require more Back, or a Buſhet of Corn, and Exact ſomewhat a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſu.</hi> Giving is taken there for Lend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and that to the Poor, as may be gather'd from the Smallneſs of the Summs; Beſides in Reality, in our Caſe, one receives no more, than he gives; for a yearly Improvement, being worth at leaſt Five <hi>per Cent.</hi> of this he's made Maſter, who receives the Principal. So that even in Compliance with the Deciſion as it lies, no more is taken than given.</p>
               <p>This is all, the Author could Pick, out of Ancient Councils, againſt which, he Apprehending length of Cuſtom had Preſcrib'd, he paſſes to later De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſions. A Tranſition which betrays, either Shallowneſs, or Prevarication, as
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:39313:52"/>to the Cauſe he undertakes, ſince Cuſtom is the beſt Interpreter of Law. Lib. 37. ff. <hi>de Legibus Optima Legum Interpres eſt Conſuetudo.</hi> Now Uſury being againſt the Law of God, no Cuſtom can pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe againſt the ſaid Law, but it has Preſcrib'd in favour of the Common Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, as he Apprehends; Therefore the Common Practice can be no Uſury, and if Cuſtom of time Paſs'd, could Preſcribe againſt the Ancient, why may not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Cuſtom Preſcribe againſt what he <hi>Quotes</hi> of Freſher <hi>Date?</hi> For that both <hi>Clergy</hi> and <hi>Regulars,</hi> take up, and put out Mony as Occaſion requires, 'tis too well Known now a days, to be denied.</p>
               <p>Little or nothing therefore to his Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, being to be gathered out of General Councils, <hi>DuTertre</hi> paſſes to Provincial Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nods In that of <hi>Milan</hi> under <hi>Pius Quartus,</hi> it is forbid to take Intereſt, upon any Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count whatſoever Yearly, <hi>for Mony of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd to be Paid in.</hi> In that of <hi>Mecklin</hi> in the time of <hi>Pius Quintut.</hi> 1566. <hi>Du Tertre</hi> ſeems to Triumph, tho' of no General Obliging Authority. Its Decree is, <hi>Syno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus Statuit &amp; ordinat ne quis Tutor,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>The Synod Decrees and Ordains that no
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:39313:52"/>Truſtee or Guardian, under Pretence of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſing the Patrimony of their</hi> Pupils, <hi>Lend the ſaid</hi> Pupills <hi>Mony to receive Yearly, a certain Lucre above the Principal, with Power of calling in the ſaid Principal, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring ſuch Bargain to be <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurious and that againſt ſuch Lenders as <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurers, to be Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded to Puniſhment, as Preſcribed by Canons.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The <hi>Synod</hi> of <hi>Milan</hi> Deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mining only as far as Cited by <hi>Du Tertre,</hi> in the Caſe <hi>Mony be offer'd to be Paid in,</hi> rather Allows, than Diſallows Intereſt for it, when not offer'd to be Pay'd in, or when it is Put out, according to the Rule, <hi>Exceptio firmat Regulum in alijs;</hi> but the <hi>Synod</hi> in expreſs Terms agrees unto it, when Granted by Law, cloſing its Prohibition, <hi>Niſi quatenus jure nominatim permittatur.</hi> In ſo much that <hi>Bonac,</hi> tho' a <hi>Milaneſe</hi> thought it not worth his while, to take notice, of what no ways oppoſes his, and our Opinion. <hi>Bail</hi> therefore the Learned compiler of Councils <hi>Tom.</hi> 2<hi>do, Pag.</hi> 492. judges the Council to be no ways in force againſt the Common Tenents; for were it, he Rightly Inſtances, <hi>Cur ergo Bonacina, &amp;
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:39313:53"/>alij Scriptores hujus Provencia, Plures exhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jaſmodi Caſibus licitos tutati ſunt ſine cujuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qam offenſione?</hi> Why then has <hi>Bonacina,</hi> and other Writers of this Province, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended many of the Caſes Mentioned in the Council, without offence to any?</p>
               <p>The <hi>Synod</hi> of <hi>Mecklin,</hi> in the ſenſe <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Tertre</hi> wrings it to, is not excepted of, in the very Province, which only it could Oblige, as appears from conſtant Practice. For my Part, I Gueſs the Decree ſtrikes, at deceitful Truſtees, and Guardians, the word under Pretext Denotes as much. They commit Uſury, in taking Mony for <hi>Lending;</hi> expreſs'd twice in the Decree, they Cloak it under a Specious Pretext, of the <hi>Orphan's</hi> Proſit, and it is no won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der if ſuch Practices be Condemn'd by the <hi>Synod.</hi> Setting aſide this or a like Gloſs; The <hi>Synod</hi> would paſs for Extravagantly Uncharitable, in forcing <hi>Orphans,</hi> to live from their Infancy, upon the Principal, to the Beggaring them, when come to Age; Wherefore even our Statute Laws, tho' Judg'd by ſome Dubious in the Point of Loan, allows the Putting out <hi>Orphan's</hi> Mony. On the other Part with what Conſcience can a Guardian expoſe his <hi>Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pil's</hi>
                  <pb n="95" facs="tcp:39313:53"/>Mony, without ſecuring the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal, and Power of calling it in?</p>
               <p>Truſtees therefore may put out their Pupil's Stock, ſo it be effectually for their Profit, as it is done without reclaim ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Church, or Magiſtrate, taking always ſuch Methods, as may exclude not only the Intention, but all appearance of Uſury. Hence <hi>Leſſius,</hi> not long aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this Synod, writing in that ſame Dioceſs makes no mention of this De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree, but juſtifies the way of Putting out Orphan's Mony; and <hi>tho', he thinks fit it ſhould be forbid for the future.</hi> I conceive, he added that Clauſe, for fear Ignorance might be an Occaſion to ſome of commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Uſury, by taking Intereſt purely for Lending, which without Uſury, might have been bargain'd for, on other Accounts, and in due forms.</p>
               <p>The Aſſemblies of <hi>Melun, Bordeaux,</hi> and <hi>Rheimes,</hi> are fully Anſwer'd, by what has been ſaid, and the Practice of all <hi>France,</hi> in Caſe of real Oppoſition, Overſways in Authority, thoſe few Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Synods.</p>
               <p>The Aſſembly of <hi>Melun, Du Tertre</hi> tells us: repeats the words of that of <hi>Milan,</hi>
                  <pb n="96" facs="tcp:39313:54"/>concluding with the Saying of Chriſt, <hi>Lend hoping nothing thereby;</hi> the like doth that of <hi>Bourdeaux.</hi> The Council of <hi>Rheimes,</hi> of greater Authority, as being approv'd by the Pope, clearly allows the Doctrin delivered hitherto of Uſury, In theſe Terms, <hi>Tit. de Faenore cum ſacra litterae excludant eum a Divino Tabernaculo, qui Pecuniam dederit ad <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſuram aperte<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> nuntient, ut mutuum Demus, nihil inde ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantes: Quiſquis praeter ſortem Praecipuam ex mutuo aliquid amplius exegerit, vel ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceperit, cujuſcunque generis illud ſit modo Pecunia eſtimari poſſit <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurarius eſſe cenſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atur.</hi> Since the Holy Scripture, excludes him from the Tabernacle, who gives his Mony to Uſury, and manifeſtly declares, <hi>That we lend hoping nothing thereby;</hi> who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ſhall Exact, or receive above the Principal of what was Lent, of what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever kind it be, ſo it be worth Mony, let him be judg'd an Uſurer. Remark well the Expreſſion, <hi>For what was Lent;</hi> there lies the Streſs: But what Council, or Aſſembly ever ſay, That Mony Put out, as in our Caſe, is <hi>Mony Lent?</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:39313:54"/>
               <head>CHAP. XV <hi>The A<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>THORITIES of Popes.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>ALexander</hi> the III. having condemn'd Uſurers in the Councils of <hi>Tours</hi> and <hi>Lateran;</hi> To the Caſe of the Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Genoa,</hi> propoſing the Dealings of ſome Merchants, who Sold dearer for retardment of Pay, writes thus: <hi>Licet contractus hujuſmodi, ex tali forma non poſſit cenſeri nomine <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurarum, nihilo mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus tamen, venditores Peccatum incurrunt, cum cogitationes hominum, omnipotenti Deo ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queant occultari.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> What could be alledg'd leſs favourable, to <hi>Du Tertre</hi>'s Purpoſe? For the Pope ſeems to excuſe from Uſury, what Divines condemns for ſuch; <hi>Tho' ſuch Contracts,</hi> ſays the Pope, <hi>as to their forms, be not to be held <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurious, yet thoſe that Sell after that Manner, ſin;</hi> whereas
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:39313:55"/>Divines, affirm to be Uſury, to take any thing for <hi>pure Delay</hi> of Payment; the ſaid Delay being eſſential to Lending. The Pope's then Meaning I take to be, that ſuch a Contract, cannot be proſecuted in the exterior Court as Uſurious; yet that ſuch Dealers, for the ordinary ſin, by forcing thoſe; who cannot give preſent Mony, to pay for the forbearance, which is plain Oppreſſion, arguing an Uſuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous intention of Gain, ſuch to have been His Holineſſes Meaning appears from the enſuing Clauſe: <hi>Since the Thoughts of Men, cannot be hidden from the Omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent God;</hi> If this wiſe Pope was ſo Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious, as not to condemn for expreſs U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury, Intereſt for pure Forbearance; Would he approve the forwardneſs of ſome, no Popes, in condemning of U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury, an Intereſt ſettled by common A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement, or by Covenants, and Titles thought juſt by Divines? One of theſe is the danger the Seller undergoes, of loſing both his Ware and Price, with the Trouble in recovering it, and that Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration on this ſcore may be taken, is not only the Opinion of <hi>Iconnes Marti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nez de Prado. Tom.</hi> 2. <hi>Theolog. Moralis,</hi>
                  <pb n="99" facs="tcp:39313:55"/>c. 27. §. 2. Citing 16 more, but before him of the Learned <hi>Sylvester,</hi> Maſter of the ſacred Palace, and eight others quoted by him, inſiſting on the Doctrin of their great Maſter, St. <hi>Tho. Opuſc.</hi> 73. c. 10. <hi>Si enim Venditor Rem ſuam,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>If a Seller intends to ſell Dearer, not for the Time only, but for the Damage like to befall him,</hi> or to redeem <hi>the Vexation, probably to be ſuffer'd, in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covering his Debt, either by Reaſon of the Malice, or Impotency of his Debtor; then he's excus'd from ſin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rban</hi> the III. three like Queſtions were Propos'd. <hi>cap. Conſuluit; Whether thoſe were to be look'd upon as <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurers, who ſold Dearer by reaſon of Staying for their Mony? Or thoſe who tacitly intended it? Or finally thoſe, who would not Releaſe the Buyer, without drawing Advantage on that Account?</hi> The Pope declares them Uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, as ſinning againſt the Command. <hi>Lend, hoping nothing therby.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Voluntary Forbearance, is equivalent to Lending; and therefore the Seller is no more oblig'd, to forbear, than to Lend; but in caſe he forbear, he doth as good as Lend, and in that
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:39313:56"/>Caſe ſins againſt Chriſt's Precept. And this is the full of the Pope's Anſwer: He makes no mention of any other Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, as the Prejudice enſuing to a Tradeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, and hinderance of Gain for want of his Mony, or the danger of no Pay, or the Loſing all; theſe are conſiderable, and it is but juſt, the Buyer ſhould make them good.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Leo</hi> the 10th. in the <hi>Lateran</hi> Council, having alledg'd Chriſt's Words. <hi>Lend hoping nothing therby:</hi> Concludes; <hi>Ea e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim eſt Propria <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurarum Interpretatio, quando videlicet ex uſu Rei quae non ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minat, de nullo labore, nullo ſumptu, nullo periculo, Lucrum fetu conquiri ſtadetur.</hi> For this is the proper Interpretation of Uſuries, <hi>viz.</hi> When one Studies to Gain, and receive Profit from things which are unfruitful, without Labour, without Expence, and without Danger.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> I ſhould think the Author had made it his Employment to cull out places, to the ſettling what he pretends to overthrow. The Pope in that Bull, ſilences the Zeal of ſuch, as impugned the Mounts of Piety, as Uſurious, hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing premis'd the Reaſons invented by
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:39313:56"/>them; of thoſe Reaſons, one is contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Words, which <hi>Du Tertre,</hi> ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by overſight, or diſingenuity, makes to be the Pope's. Whereas His Holineſs, having related the Arguments of ſuch, as diſapprov'd of the Mounts of Piety, as Uſurious, encourages the erecting of them, by granting Indulgencies; And who ſhall either by word or writing, Preach or Diſpute againſt them, he makes liable to the Puniſhment of Excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication. <hi>Latae ſententiae, nullo obſtante Privilegio.</hi> That is, <hi>Ipſo facto,</hi> to be incurr'd no Priviledge whatſoveer withſtanding it. What greater evidence of this Pope's Judgment of the invalidity of their Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and amongſt the reſt of this ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected, which <hi>Du Tertre</hi> inconſiderately brings for the Pope's, tho' rejected by His Holineſs. But <hi>Du Tertre</hi> would ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear ſome Body.</p>
               <p>To anſwer Reaſon with Reaſon. That Mony cannot fructify, has often been denied, and is apparently untrue, in the Gain to be made in Purchaſing good Pennyworths; inſomuch after all, <hi>Du Tertre</hi> himſelf, <hi>Pag.</hi> 134, and 135. acknowledges that Saying to be verified
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:39313:57"/>only of <hi>Mony Lent,</hi> which being no more the Lender's, but the Borrowers, can yield nothing to the Lender; By reaſon, <hi>Res fructificat Domino.</hi> The thing fruits to its Owner, and ſo far he is in the Right; but ſeems not to reflect, that it may fructify before 'tis Lent, and then to Bargain for what it may yield, is no <hi>Lending,</hi> nor <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury.</hi> Nor is it without Labour, Expences, and Danger, that Mony is Lett out. What Labour in Get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting it? In Preſerving it? To omit leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer Cares and Troubles, in drawing up Deeds, Counting? <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The want of its Profit, Is it not a ſort of Charges? The danger of Damage, the Expoſer of his Mony, takes upon himſelf, which may happen from frequent Caſualties, for want of his Mony, as in Accidents of Fire, Sickneſs, Impriſonments, War, or the like; Is it not very Senſible? And where is the Principal? And yet by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of thoſe very Divines, no <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury</hi> where ſuch Cauſes intervene.</p>
               <p>But <hi>Greg.</hi> the 9th, even excludes even the <hi>Danger of Loſing the Principal,</hi> from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a good Title. <hi>Cap. Naviganti vel e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unti ad Nundinas,</hi> &amp;c. The Perſon Lend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:39313:57"/>a certain Summ of Mony, to one that Puts to Sea, or go's to a Fair, receiving ſomewhat above the Capital for taking upon himſelf the Danger, is to be judg'd an Uſurer.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> How doth this cohere with the Objection of the Precedent pretended Authority? There 'tis required there be no danger; Here, even in caſe of Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, 'tis made Uſury to take Intereſt. <hi>Bernartius</hi> cited by <hi>Laym.</hi> n. 13. <hi>de <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſura.</hi> ſuſpects a Miſtake of Print, by the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of a <hi>Non.</hi> So that in the place of <hi>is to be judg'd,</hi> ought to be read, <hi>is not to be judg'd.</hi> This is clearly gather'd from the Connexion, as you may ſee there. If this like you not, e'en take the words as they lie. He that Lends ventures the Danger of Loſing; ſo that to Bargain for that Danger, by way of Inſurance, is either not to Lend, or taking for the Danger of what is Lent, is Uſury.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Innocent</hi> the 3d. <hi>Declares <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury to be againſt both Teſtaments.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> We ſay 'tis alſo againſt the Law of Nature, and by its being ſo, we have evinced, that the Putting out Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, as in Practice, is no <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="104" facs="tcp:39313:58"/>
               <p>To make an end of tiring my Reader with theſe and like Citations; <hi>Cuſtom,</hi> the beſt interpreter of Authority, and the <hi>Definition</hi> of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury,</hi> by which all <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury</hi> muſt be tried, are fully ſufficient, to ſolve whatever Objection. I have not made it my Buſineſs to trace <hi>Du Tertre,</hi> ſtep by ſtep, he is ever upon the wing, and rather flutters, than walks to amuſe with the Noiſe of his <hi>Prones,</hi> where he cannot convince with Reaſon, himſelf Preſumptuous, inflicts that Character, upon three Divines of Known Ability, <hi>Medicina, Leſſius, Valentia, Pag.</hi> 138. where he abuſes his Reader, by impoſing upon <hi>Leſſius</hi> very groſly, as will appear to the Examiner, from whence I gueſs, how he treats the others, which I have not by me. To what purpoſe, <hi>Pag.</hi> 145. doth he unite Oppoſits, as <hi>Leſſius,</hi> and <hi>Valentia,</hi> with the Author of the Letter he impugns? Is itany wiſe aſtoniſhing, that Oppoſits ſhould contradict one another? His inference, that the Danger of the Principal is greater, when in the hands of the Poor; therefore more may be taken from them, than of the Rich, is a pure Inference of his own Brain,
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:39313:58"/>without Premiſes. Who commits any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable Summs to the Poor, and knows he not that Intereſt tax'd by Law, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be exceeded; and that this only in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſes, as the Sums putt out do, leſs for little Sums, and more for greater? The Law therefore is favourable to the Poor, where the Danger of the Principal is greater.</p>
               <p>Who will not ſmile at the Man's E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquent Simplicity, <hi>Pag.</hi> 144? Where after pretenſions to Univerſality, after having in one Leaf, no leſs than thrice rallied up Fathers, Popes, and Councils, by way of Crowning all he tells you, That <hi>many Learned Doctors of</hi> Sorbon, <hi>and of the Faculty of Divinity of</hi> Paris, <hi>among which, were the moſt Illuſtrious Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rats of that great City have Signed the Common Sentiment of the Church in the Matter of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury.</hi> I ſuppoſe in Condemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the common Practice.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Was it their Signing that made it common? Or if common before, what need of their Signing? They Sign'd then what was not common to all, and what he would make common. But how? By the Signing of Many. He ſays, not by the Signing of all; he ſays not of the
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:39313:59"/>greateſt Part, the oppoſit then, might be as common, as what they Sign'd. Many Doctors therefore, and they Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors of the <hi>Sorbon</hi> too; Many Curats, and they Curats of <hi>Paris</hi> too, with whole Towns, and Provinces in <hi>France,</hi> pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſing what he abuſively ſtiles Uſury, are of poiſe enough, not only to coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ballance, but ſo outweigh the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of his many Doctors and Curats, as to the common Senſe of the Church. And the Biſhops of <hi>France,</hi> Are they to be ſlighted, becauſe ſilent Lovers of Peace, and Enemies of Novelty? Can they be thought to be leſs concern'd for the good of Souls, or leſs knowing than ſome Curats of <hi>Paris?</hi> And their Silence, is it not a loud rebuke, to his Many? And the Divines of other Nations, Are they to paſs for Shadows? With all reſpect due to the <hi>Sorbon,</hi> be it ſaid, o'ther Countries, have given, and daily afford to the World, Men as Eminent for Learning; Why not then to be relied on, as well as his Many? For which we have his bare Word. <hi>England</hi> alone has oftner given Maſters to the <hi>Sorbon,</hi> than the <hi>Sorbon</hi> to <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="107" facs="tcp:39313:59"/>
               <p>Perchance <hi>Du Tertre</hi> might have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted, as ſome of late have done, upon the Propoſitions condemn'd by <hi>Innocent</hi> the 11th, <hi>Anno.</hi> 1679. I therefore ſet them down, leaving to the Reader, to judge how far they affect our Caſe.</p>
               <p>The 24th Propoſition runs thus: <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſura non eſt, dum aliquid ultra ſortem exigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, tanquam ex Benevolentia, &amp; gratitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dine debitum, ſed tantum ſi exigatur, tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam debitum ex Juſtitia.</hi> 'Tis no Uſury if ſomething above the Principal be exacted, as due by way of Benevolency, and Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, but only as exacted by way of Juſtice.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Propoſition is deſervedly condemn'd, and condemns it ſelf. For a Benevolence, or ſpontaneous Act of Gratitude, cannot be ſaid properly to be Due, and therefore to Exact it as Due, is Injuſtice; and if for the Uſe of a Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal Lent, 'tis Uſury. To receive a Benevolence, or Gift by way of Grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, is not condemned? Nay to Exact a Gift once made, is not even Injuſtice, it being his, to whom it is given; now by the general Agreement this Gift is made, antecedently to the Putting out Mony,
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:39313:60"/>it may therefore be required; Beſides, the Propoſition reaches none of the foremen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned ways, or Titles, for which Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt is Due, by way of Juſtice.</p>
               <p>The 41. Propoſition is: <hi>Cum Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuata Pecunia ſit Precioſior numeranda, &amp; nullus ſit qui non Majoris faciat Pecuniam Preſentem quam futuram, poteſt Creditor aliquid ultra ſortem a Mutuatario exigere, &amp; eo titulo excuſari.</hi> Since Mony Lent, is better than Mony to be Pay'd, and that there is no Body, who doth not eſteem Preſent Mony, more than future, the Creditor upon that Account, may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire ſomething above the Principal, from the Borrower, and ſo be excus'd from Uſury.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Condemnations being <hi>ſtricti Juris,</hi> fall upon Propoſitions Preciſely as they lie; Now this Propoſition taken as it is worded, is both Scandalous and falſe. For one that Lends, parts with preſent Mony, upon future repay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, a token they are equal, at leaſt, in his eſteem. Is he no Body? Beſides, dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of time, alters not the worth of Mony Whence it enſues that to ground a Title of receiving Intereſt, upon ſo
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:39313:60"/>clear an untruth, and Futurity of repay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, eſſential to Lending, is to excuſe taking Intereſt for Lending, which is Scandalous, and therefore juſtly Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned.</p>
               <p>To the aforeſaid Propoſitions, may be added the 47th. Among thoſe Condemn'd by <hi>Alex.</hi> the 7th. <hi>Licitum eſt mutuanti ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid ultra ſortem exigere ſi ſe Obliget ad non repetendam. ſortem uſque ad certum Tempus.</hi> 'Tis Lawful for a Lender, to Exact ſomething above the Principal, provided he Oblige himſelf, not to call it Back, for a Set time.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Who ſees not, that ſuch a Len<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der would have Intereſt, for a pure For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearance, which is Flat Uſury, as we have often Affirm'd, and follows from its Definition. So that the Propoſitions Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn'd by the late <hi>Popes,</hi> leave our Caſe untouched. And no ways oppoſe what has been ſaid for the Lawfulneſs, of Putting out Mony, conſider'd as was Promiſed, as to the Law of Nature, Scripture, and Church.</p>
               <p>I ſhould not have Concern'd my Self in an Anſwer to Monſieur <hi>Du Tertre</hi>'s Book, long ſince Printed, and I Queſtion
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:39313:61"/>not, but already Anſwer'd, by ſome of his own Nation, had not his Genius paſs'd the Seas, and appear'd with no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Weapons than his, to the Terror of Timorous Souls, and perplexing of Conſciences.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XVII. The <hi>CONCL<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SION.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TO Conclude as I Prefac'd. Having preſented the Reader, according to Promiſe, with what your Reformers, in the Point of Putting out Mony, have to ſay to Us, and we in Anſwer to them, let Him call a Jury, of his Impartial Thoughts, to the Caſe of Putting out Mony, and upon Evidence, brought in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it, let him Condemn it, of Uſury. But if no Evidence appears, Poſſeſſion of its Innocency ſtill holds, Ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in Agreement, and Cuſtom, upheld by Judges, Juſtified by Divines, upon ſeveral Titles, and generally Practis'd. If Scripture, Church, and Fathers in
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:39313:61"/>veighing againſt Uſury, reflect not up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it, if the Law of Nature diſallows it not, let it be clear'd at the Barr, of unby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſs'd Reaſon. Let the Practiſers make Conſcience, of Real Sins; let them of their Juſt Gains, be Charitable to the Needy; let them hope no Increaſe for <hi>Lend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> but from God, yet at the ſame time; they are Rightly inform'd, they have no Obligation of Prejudicing themſelves, but a Duty to Improve Honeſtly the Talents God has left with them, by Put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them out at an eaſy Rate. It is a ſer vice they owe to the Publick, for which we are Born. Such as Scrupuliſe at it; let them much more make Conſcience of judging others. Let them be Careful, leſt upon Surmiſes of Uſury, or rather under a falſe Pretext, they become Slaves of Avarice, make their Coffers <hi>Temples,</hi> and Mony their <hi>Idols;</hi> by ſo doing, they Clip the Common Stock; ſo that the Share they have, goes no more, they caſt Trade into a Deep Conſumption, by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priving it, of its Nouriſhment, and wholly Croſs the deſign of the General welfare of a Nation, Mantain'd by a Circulation of Mony, as our Bodies are, by a Circula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Blood.</p>
               <pb n="112" facs="tcp:39313:62"/>
               <p>No leſs Zeal was ſhown, by ſome Preachers, and Divines, againſt the <hi>Mounts</hi> of Piety, than ſince has been, by a few others, againſt Putting out of Mony; When the <hi>Pope</hi> Heading a Council, in regard of the Poor; and Common Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities, judg'd fit not only to Curb it, but when Tranſported either to Words, or Writing, to Excomunicate it as a Diſquiet to the Chriſtian world, The Rule of Law, <hi>Quod qui commodum ſentit, onus quoque ſentire debet,</hi> on which the <hi>Pope</hi> and Council appear to ground themſelves, is of no leſs Force in our Caſe: The Rule is: <hi>That he who Partakes of a Conveniency, ought alſo to ſhare of the Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den annex'd to it.</hi> It is for Conveniency Mony is taken up, the Burden annex'd to it, is Intereſt, which for Juſt Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, the Law judges Reaſonable. It were a Piece of Signal Temerity, to Queſtion the ſaid <hi>Mounts</hi> of Piety, and if the Common Practiſe have the ſame Reaſon, even with ſome advantage, were it not too Ventureſome, to Condemn it? Would not the Cenſure by Parity of Reaſon, equally affect both? And were not this to forfeit, the Reſpect, and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:39313:62"/>due to Popes, the <hi>Lateran</hi> Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil, and Chriſtendom in General? The ends of the Mounts of Piety, is to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve ſuch as Neceſſity compels to take up Mony at exorbitant Rates; This alſo is Provided for, by the common Practice, tho not ſo fully, it being not eaſy to find Mony to take up; whereas the ſaid Mounts are ever ready to Supply; on which Account they are to be wiſhed for in this Realm. The Mounts of Piety, towards the Maintenance of Neceſſaries, receive ſomewhat more, than Current Intereſt; with Current Intereſt alone, the common Practice contents it ſelf, the Mounts are ſecured of their Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal; the eommon Practice for moſt part leaves it Hazardous. Is it the taking leſs? Is it the Hazard that creats Uſury? If not, How can that Guilt be charged upon the common Practice, and not the Mounts of Piety? And to reflect upon them as Uſurious, Doth it not betoken unduti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulneſs, and more want of Charity, than proviſion of true Zeal, more Temerity, than Prudence.</p>
               <p>The ſimplicity of the Dove, is to be guided by the Prudence of the Serpento
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:39313:63"/>
                  <hi>Believe not every Spirit,</hi> (ſays St. <hi>John, 1 Epiſt. Chap.</hi> 4.) Too much Auſterity of Doctrine, favours more of Affecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, than Diſcretion, and drives oftner at Libertiniſm, than true Reform, every one inclining to ſhake off the Yoke, who rendred too heavy. Exceſs of Rigor is a kind of Uſury, in that it extorts upon Conſcience to the Oppreſſion of a weak Brother. The way to Heaven is narrow, we ought not to ſtreighten it more; nor to lay ſtumbling blocks in the way.</p>
               <p>This was the Senſe of the moſt Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and Illuſtrious Order of St. <hi>Dominick,</hi> in the Gloſs upon the Prologue, to their Conſtitutions, <hi>Tex.</hi> 1. §. 3. to thoſe Words, <hi>Cum Ordo Noster,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ramus,</hi> &amp;c. Say they, <hi>We declare, That three things Chiefly hinder the ſaving of Souls; of theſe, the Third is too much Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gor, and Auſterity in Counſels, and Opinions, or Men are ſo terrified with them, as to neglect the Salvation of their Souls; wherefore Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gor and Severity, are to be Relented, as much as may be, and Men are to be Treated with Benignity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yet nearer to our Purpoſe the great Son of ſo Wiſe, and Religious a Parent,
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:39313:63"/>St. <hi>Tho. qudl.</hi> 9. <hi>Art.</hi> 15. In Corp Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes it thus: <hi>Omnis Queſtio, in qua de Peccato Morali quaeritur,</hi> &amp;c. 'Tis dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous to decide a Queſtion, treating of a Mortal Sin; if no expreſs Truth ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears; by reaſon the Error, by which it is apprehended to be mortal, what is not mortal, binds under Mortal. The expreſs Truth againſt the Common Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, has not yet been diſcovered.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Du Tertre</hi> therefore, and thoſe of his Humor, ſhould have taken and Con'd the Leſſon, being of ſo high Importance, given them by the Renowned Chancellor, <hi>John Gerſon, lib.</hi> 4. <hi>de Vita ſpirituali. Littera. O.</hi> pag. 3. <hi>Doctores Theologo,</hi> &amp;c. Doctors of Divinity, muſt not eaſily conclude certain Actions, or Omiſſions, to be mortal Sins; for by ſuch Wilful, Rigid, Hard, and too ſtrict Aſſertions, Men are never drawn out of the Mire of Sin, but are plung'd into another, deeper, becauſe more Deſperate. To what Purpoſe then to render more bitter, and heavy the Yoke of Chriſt, which is ſweet, and the Burden which is light?</p>
               <p>This had been much to <hi>Du Tertre</hi>'s Purpoſe, and perchance might have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay'd
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:39313:64"/>his too fervorous Rigor; when, <hi>Pag.</hi> 172. he pretends with a Scrap or two of a holy Father, to block up the way to Heaven, and to exclude all Merchants, and Tradeſmen from Eternal Bliſs. And i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> not this to endeavour to render Salvation and God's Precepts Morally impoſſible? Or at leaſt as impoſſible, as it is for Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Society to be maintained without Merchandizing and Commerce? Doth it not reflect upon Providence, as Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhing a Religion incoherent with all Trading, ſo neceſſary co the Welfare and Preſervation of Mankind? It is a Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar Genius rules his Pen; Whether for love of Novelty, or to appear ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>body in the World, or out of miſtaken. Zeal, to correct what needs no Amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, it is not for me to decide. As to my ſelf, whatever I have writ in De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of the Common Practice, I ſhall entirely ſubmit to better Reaſon, it is my Duty ſo to do; and having done what I thought my Duty, to the quieting of Conſcience, in the Caſe of putting out Mony, I end.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
